<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="88"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[WELCOME ADDRESS BY THE CHAIR OF THE
                               ORGANIZING COMMITTEE

                         th
                    THE 4  INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON INNOVATIVE
                            RESEARCH ACROSS DISCIPLINES 2021

                                          rd
                                      nd
                                Bali | 2  – 3  NOVEMBER 2021

               Om  Swastyastu,  AssalamualaikumWr.Wb.  Syalom,  Namo  budaya,    Salam
               Harmoni, best wishes for all of us.

               Good Morning, and welcome to the ICIRAD 2021 (International Conference on
               Innovative Research Across Discipline)

               The  most  honorable,  Rector  of  Universitas  Pendidikan  Ganesha  and  The
               President of Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University.
               The most honorable, the keynote and invited speakers Prof. Dor Abrahamson,
               Ph.D., Dr. Gede Rasben Dantes, Dr. Nora Oredina, Dewi  A. Padmo, Ph.D and
               Prof. Dr. Ahmad Djojosugito, dr., SpOT(K), MHA, MBA

               First, let us send our profound gratitude upon Tuhan Yang Maha Esa/ Ida Sang
               Hyang  Widhi  Wasa,  the  Almighty  God,  for  His  blessings  of  the  opportunity  to
               have this event, the 4th International Conference on Innovative Research Across
               Disciplines (ICIRAD 2021). It is my honor and pleasure as Chairman of this event
               to welcome you all.
               This conference is organized by the Research and Community Service Institute
               of  Universitas  Pendidikan  Ganesha  in  partnership  with  Don  Mariano  Marcos
               Memorial  State  University  as  a  platform  for  cross-discipline  studies  among
               international  researchers  and  scholars  across  the  world.  In  this  year,  this
               conference  carrying  the  theme  “Enhancing  Sustainable  Development  Through
               Innovation and Creativity”.
               In  This  event  attended  by  over  150  presenters  with  60  abstract  submissions.
               Those  participants  come  from  3  different  countries:  Indonesia,  Philiphine,  and
               Amerika.we also began targeting proceedings published by Atlantis Press.
               Finally, it is a privilege to serve as ICIRAD 2021 Chairman in these exciting times
               Hopefully  the  4th  ICIRAD  conference  in  2021  can  provide  benefits  and
               contributions to us, and the wider community. We would like to thank all those
               who  have  contributed  to  the  implementation  of  this  conference.  Enjoy  the
               conference


                                                Singaraja, 3 November 2021
                                                Chairman of the committee



                                                M. Rudi Irwansyah

                                                                           1]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Rundown of the 4  ICIRAD 2021
                                                th


               Day 1: Tuesday, 2  November 2021
                                   nd
              Time                            Program
           07:30 – 08:00  Preparation (Participants are admitted to the virtual room)
           08:00 – 09:00  Opening Ceremony
                           •   Indonesian National Anthem
                           •   Philippine National Anthem
                           •   Prayer
                           •   Chairman of the Committee Report
                           •   Opening Remark from Rector of Universitas Pendidikan
                               Ganesha
                           •   Message from President of DMMMSU
                           •   Profile Video of Undiksha
                           •   Profile Video of DMMMSU
                           •   Photo Session
           09:00 – 10:30  Plenary Session 1:
                           •   Keynote Speaker 1 : Dor Abrahamson, Ph.D. (University of
                               California, Berkeley)
                           •   Keynote Speaker 2 : Dr. Gede Rasben Dantes, S.T., M.TI.
                               (Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Bali Indonesia)

                          Moderator : Dr.rer.nat. I Gusti Ngurah Agung Suryaputra, S.T, M.Sc.
           10:30 – 10:45  Token of Appreciation + Photo Session

           10:45 – 11:30   Plenary Session 2 :
                           •   Keynote Speaker 3 : Dr. Nora A. Oredina (Don Mariano
                               Marcos Memorial State University, The Philipines)

                       Moderator : Made Windu Antara Kesiman, S.T., M.Sc., Ph.D.
           11:30 – 11:45  Token of Appreciation + Photo Session

           11:45 – 13:00  Lunch Break
           13:00 – 15:45  Parallel Session 1 (3 Breakout Rooms)

               WITA = BALI TIME
                                             2]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Day 2: Wednesday, 3  November 2021
                                      rd
                 Time                          Program
              08:30 – 09:00   Preparation (Participants are admitted to the virtual room)
              09:00 – 09:45   Plenary Session 3:
                               •   Invited  Speaker  1:  Dewi  A.  Padmo  Putri,  M.A.,
                                   Ph.D (Universitas Terbuka, Indonesia)

                            Moderator : Mark Kristian C. Ledda

              09:45 – 09:50   Token of Appreciation + Photo Session

              09:50 – 10:35   Plenary Session 4:
                               •   Invited Speaker 2: Prof. Dr. M. Ahmad Djojosugito,
                                   dr. Sp.OT(K), MHA, MBA (Universitas Pendidikan
                                   Ganesha, Bali Indonesia)

                            Moderator : Rhoda M. Lilan

              10:35 – 10:45   Token of Appreciation + Photo Session

              10:45 – 13:30   Parallel Session 2 (3 Breakout Rooms)
              13:30 – 14:00   Closing Ceremony


               WITA = BALI TIME












                                             3]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Ground Rules for the 4  ICIRAD 2021
                                                   th

                a)  Participants are advised to enter the virtual room 30 minutes before the
                   opening ceremony.
                b)  Please rename your zoom name according to Breakout Room and your paper
                   ID. This is important for admitting participants to the virtual room as well as to
                   breakout room.
                   Example:

                   [Breakout Room]_Paper ID]_[Name]

                   A_102_Gede Santika Wirateja
                c)  The committee will stop admitting participants to the virtual room during the
                   opening ceremony to prevent the distraction. After it finishes, other
                   participants may enter the virtual room.
                d)  Presenters are given 10 minutes to present (either using video or directly) and
                   5 minutes to respond to question from the other participants if any. Video
                   presentation will be played by the operator in that room.
                e)  During the presentations, participants’ audio are muted. Should you have any
                   questions, there will be discussion session at the end of each presentation. In
                   the discussion session, participants may write down the questions on the chat
                   box or click the “raise hand” feature on zoom. Those who are admitted by the
                   moderator or chair may deliver their questions directly.
                f)   The link for the attendance form will be provided for opening ceremony and
                   parallel sessions. It will be sent by the committee during the session.

               Participants are expected to attend all of the agenda during the conference.









                                             4]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Parallel Session 1
                              Day 1: Tuesday, 2  November 2021
                                            nd
                                     Breakout Room A
                           Session Chair : Ni Putu Novita Puspa Dewi
            No      Time     ID          Author                 Title

             1   13.00 - 13.15   2   Kadek Suranata, Itsar Bolo   Psychometric Properties
                                 Rangka, I Putu Agus    of The Indonesian
                                 Apriliana, Wayan Eka   Version Students Well-
                                 Paramartha, I Ketut    Being Scale: A
                                 Dharsana and Ifdil Ifdil   Confirmatory Factor
                                                        Analysis
             2   13.15 - 13.30   41  Gede Nugraha Sudarsana   Identification of Individual
                                 and Ni Ketut Suarni    Intolerance Behavior
                                                        Trends Through Thematic
                                                        Apperception Test (TAT)
                                                        Analysis
             3   13.30 - 13.45   21  M. Rudi Irwansyah, Made   Exploring Student
                                 Ary Meitriana and Ni'Matul   Academic Procrastination
                                 Istiqomah              Based on Time
                                                        Management, Social
                                                        Support and Self-Efficacy
             4   13.45 - 14.00   32  Ni Ketut Suarni, Gede   TBLA-Based Reflective
                                 Nugraha Sudarsana, I   Learning Model Analysis
                                 Wayan Sujana, Ketut    is Effective as a
                                 Susiani and I Gusti Agung   Technique for
                                 Ayu Wulandari          Strengthening Students
                                                        Pattern of Learning
             5   14.00 - 14.15   12  Luh Masdarini and Ida Ayu   The Influence of Social
                                 Putu Hemy Ekayani      Attitude on Cognitive
                                                        Competence and
                                                        Practices in Learning
                                                        Governance Courses on
                                                        Family Welfare Education
                                                        Students
             6   14.15 - 14.30   10  Ketut Chandra Adinata   The Practicality of D-
                                 Kusuma, I Wayan        MENBOLA : Interactive
                                 Artanayasa and Adrianus I   Learning Media In Higher
                                 Wayan Ilia Yuda Sukmana   Education
                                             5]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[7   14.30 - 14.45   23  Ida Bagus Putrayasa and   The Essays of Fourth
                                 Dewa Putu Ramendra     Grade Elementary School
                                                        Students: A Syntactic
                                                        Study Based on
                                                        Character Education
                                                        Values
             8   14.45 - 15.00   53  I Gusti Ayu Diah Gita   The Representation of
                                 Saraswati, Ni Komang Arie   Character Education in
                                 Suwastini, Ida Ayu Made   the Characterization of
                                 Istri Utami, Ni Luh Putu Sri   Lily Owens in Sue Monk
                                 Adnyani and I Gusti Agung   Kidd’s The Secret Life of
                                 Sri Rwa Jayantini      Bees (2001)
             9   15.00 – 15.15   49  Ida Bagus Putu Arnyana   The Implementation of Tri
                                 and Ida Ayu Made Istri   Hita Karana Culture-
                                 Utami                  Based Character
                                                        Education at Pasraman
                                                        Budi Pekerti, Kemenuh
                                                        Village, Bali
            10  15.15 – 15.30   57  Arnie G Dizon       Content Analysis of the K
                                                        to 12 World History
                                                        Teaching Guides in terms
                                                        of Teaching Approaches
            11  15.30 – 15.45   4   Nyoman Wijana and Sanusi  Development of
                                 Mulyadiharja           Textbooks Based on
                                                        Research in the
                                                        Perspective of Education
                                                        and Tourism
                                                        Development in the Bukit
                                                        Kangin Forest, Tenganan
                                                        Pegringsingan
                                     Parallel Session 1
                                     Breakout Room B
                            Session Chair : Ida Ayu Made Istri Utami
            No      Time     ID          Author                 Title

             1   13.00 - 13.15   25  I Gde Wawan Sudatha and   How is the Instructional
                                 Adrianus I Wayan Ilia Yuda   Video Development
                                 Sukmana                Process with Dynamic
                                                        Drawing Principles?
             2   13.15 - 13.30   30  I Wayan Kertih, I Gede   Empowerment of

                                             6]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Astra Wesnawa, I Putu   Balinese Local Wisdom
                                 Sriartha, and Tuty Maryati,   and Important Elements
                                 M.Pd.                  of Community Life as
                                                        Learning Sources in Of
                                                        IPS SMP/MTs. In
                                                        Buleleng Regency
             3   13.30 - 13.45   38  Anak Agung Gede Agung, I   Developing a Student
                                 Made Yudana, I Gusti Ketut   Management Model
                                 Arya Sunu, Kadek Rihendra  Based on Balinese Local
                                 Dantes, and I Gde Wawan   Wisdom
                                 Sudatha
             4   13.45 - 14.00   43  Wahjoedi, I Putu Panca Adi   Development of Tourism
                                 and Damiati            Master Plan in Panji
                                                        Anom Village, Sukasada
                                                        District, Buleleng
                                                        Regency
             5   14.00 - 14.15   20  Made Agus Dharmadi and   Analysis of The Maintain
                                 A.A                    of Bali Traditional Games
                                 Yudha Martin Mahardika   Through Photos and
                                                        Videos of Games to
                                                        Improve Digital Literacy
             6   14.15 - 14.30   27  Ni Wayan Sukerti and   A Development of
                                 Cokorda Istri Raka Marsiti   Chinese And Japanese
                                                        Culinary Teaching
                                                        Materials In Asia Culinary
                                                        Courses
             7   14.30 - 14.45   28  Ni Wayan Sukerti, Cokorda   The Implementation of
                                 Istri Raka Marsiti, Luh   Fussion Food Teaching
                                 Masdarini and Damiati   Materials Based on Local
                                                        Bali Food in Vocational
                                                        High School Students in
                                                        Culinary Expertise
             8   14.45 - 15.00   50  I Gede Astra Wesnawa,   Forms of Rural Tourism
                                 Putu Indra Christiawan and   and Creative Economy
                                 Luh Gede Erni Sulindawati   Development
             9   15.00 – 15.15   52  Luh Putu Santiari, Sariyasa   Analysis of Archives
                                 and I Ketut Ngurah     Management at
                                 Arintasuta             Universitas Pendidikan
                                                        Ganesha
            10  15.15 – 15.30   22  Putu Krisna Adwitya   Sustainable Forests in
                                 Sanjaya and I Komang   Bali: Factors That Affect It
                                             7]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Arthana                (Semi Log Model
                                                        Analysis)
            11  15.30 – 15.45   63  William S. Gayo, Jr.   Congruence Properties of
                                                        the Sum of Positive
                                                        Powers of two Mersenne
                                                        Primes
                                     Parallel Session 1
                                     Breakout Room C
                         Session Chair : A.A.N Yudha Martin Mahardika
            No      Time     ID          Author                 Title

             1   13.00 - 13.15   17  Ni Luh Putu Sri Adnyani, Ni   The Development of a
                                 Made Rai Wisudariani, I   Trilingual Dictionary for
                                 Nyoman Pasek           Elementary Students
                                 Hadisaputra, Ni Komang
                                 Arie Suwastini and Putu
                                 Wiraningsih
             2   13.15 - 13.30   19  Ni Luh Putu Sri Adnyani,   The Development of an
                                 Gede Aditra Pradnyana, Ni   Android-Based Kata
                                 Made Rai Wisudariani, I   Kolok Sign Language
                                 Made Ardwi Pradnyana and  Dictionary
                                 Gede Rasben Dantes
             3   13.30 - 13.45   33  Luh Gede Eka Wahyuni and  Enhancing EFL Students’
                                 Ni Putu Astiti Pratiwi   Speaking Competency
                                                        Through Animated
                                                        Learning Video
             4   13.45 - 14.00   34  I Nyoman Adi Jaya Putra,   Boosting The Quality of
                                 Putu Kerti Nitiasih, Ni Luh   EFL Class through
                                 Putu Era Adnyayanti and   HOTS-based English
                                 Luh Gd. Rahayu Budiarta   Activity Book: Upgrading
                                                        Independent Active Class
                                                        during Pandemic
             5   14.00 - 14.15   35  Karina Wedhanti, Dewa Ayu  A Need Analysis in
                                 Eka Agustini, I Nyoman   English Material for XI
                                 Pasek Hadi Saputra and I   Grade of Beauty Program
                                 Putu Ngura Wage        at SMK N 2 Singaraja
                                 Myartawan
             6   14.15 - 14.30   36  Putu Kerti Nitiasih, Luh Gd   Developing Students’
                                 Rahayu Budiarta and Ni   Worksheet HOTS-Based
                                 Luh Putu Era Adnyayanti   English Learning for

                                             8]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Fourth Grade Students of
                                                        Elementary School
             7   14.30 - 14.45   39  A.A. Gede Yudha    Readability of English
                                 Paramartha, Ni Luh Putu   Teacher Assessment
                                 Eka Sulistia Dewi and Luh   Literacy Instrument in
                                 Gede Eka Wahyuni       Indonesian Context
             8   14.45 - 15.00   58  Abelynn T. Llarenas   Narrativizing Student
                                                        Teachers’ Experiences of
                                                        Teaching English Abroad
             9   15.00 – 15.15   54  Ni Komang Arie Suwastini,   Why Students Should
                                 Luh Winda Agustina, Putu   Like to Have Severus
                                 Yasamahadewi, Ronald   Snape as A Teacher?
                                 Umbas, I Gusti Ayu Agung
                                 Dian Susanthi and Nice
                                 Maylani Asril
            10  15.15 – 15.30   5   Desak Made Sri Mardani   How is The Learning
                                 and I Wayan Sadyana    Process and Assessment
                                                        in E-Learning According
                                                        to Japanese High
                                                        School/Vocational High
                                                        School Teachers in Bali
            11  15.30 – 15.45   67  Jomar L Aban        Understanding the
                                                        Pedagogical Dilemma
                                                        Using the KAP
                                                        (Knowledge, Attitude and
                                                        Practice) Approach:
                                                        “What Will You Use?”














                                             9]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Parallel Session 2
                             Day 2: Wednesday, 3  November 2021
                                             rd
                                     Breakout Room D
                          Session Chair : Dewa Ayu Puteri Handayani
            No      Time     ID          Author                 Title

             1   10.45 - 11.00   47  I Gede Sudirtha, I Gede   Interaction Patterns of
                                 Partha Sindu, Agus Aan   SMA/SMK Students in
                                 Jiwa Permana and Irwan   Buleleng Regency Based
                                 Nur                    on Learning Styles in
                                                        Online Learning Using
                                                        LMS and Social Media
             2   11.00 - 11.15   48  I Wayan Sutaya, Ketut Udy   Analysis and Simulation
                                 Ariawan and I Gede     of Current Zero Crossing
                                 Nurhayata              Time Interval Under
                                                        Different Loads
             3   11.15 - 11.30   14  Made Windu Antara   Development of Mobile
                                 Kesiman, Kadek Teguh   Based Application for
                                 Dermawan and Gede Aditra  Balinese Lontar Image
                                 Pradnyana              Transliteration
             4   11.30 - 11.45   24  Ni'Matul Istiqomah, Nur   Self-Managed Learning in
                                 Anita Yunikawati and M.   Online Learning
                                 Rudi Irwansyah
             5   11.45 - 12.00   26  I Gde Wawan Sudatha and   Implementation Of
                                 Anak Agung Gede Agung   Project-Based E-Learning
                                                        in Courses Description
                                                        Statistics During Covid-19
             6   12.00 - 12.15   37  Putu Adi Krisna Juniarta   Mobile Assisted
                                 and Dewa Komang Tantra   Language Learning in
                                                        Distance Learning:
                                                        Learning Process And
                                                        Students’ Perception
             7   12.15 - 12.30   46  Agus Aan Jiwa Permana   Home Care Service
                                 and I Gede Partha Sindu   Application for Patients
             8   12.30 - 12.45   61  Dr. Stephan Kupsch   Determining a Vigorous
                                                        Beehive Location thru
                                                        Computer Vision
                                                        Technology
             9   12.45 – 13.00   64  Ana Liza O. Ordinario   Technology And
                                                        Livelihood Education
                                             10]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Program Of DMMMSU:
                                                        Analysis And
                                                        Enhancement
            10  13.00 – 13.15   13  Adnyana Putra and Made   Relationship Between
                                 Kurnia Widiastuti Giri   Discussion Activity and
                                                        Try-Out on Learning
                                                        Outcomes of Medical
                                                        Students
            11  13.15 – 13.30   69  Maria Elaine D Pinay-An,   English Grammar
                                 Rochelle M Verganio and   Proficiency of English
                                 Desiree E Donato       Major College Students in
                                                        the Philippines
                                     Parallel Session 2
                                     Breakout Room E
                           Session Chair : Ni Putu Novita Puspa Dewi
            No      Time     ID          Author                 Title


             1   10.45 - 11.00   1   Made Kurnia Widiastuti Giri,  Improve immunity by
                                 I Wayan Muderawan,     doing Yoga Asanas as
                                 Komang Hendra Setiawan,   Spiritual Healing : A
                                 Ketut Indra Purnomo and   Review
                                 Putu Arya Nugraha
             2   11.00 - 11.15   18  Muhammad Rizki Fauzi,   The Stiffness of Virus
                                 Nurfa Risha, Gede Aris   Shell: Influenza Lipid
                                 Gunadi and Luh Putu Budi   Shell
                                 Yasmini
             3   11.15 - 11.30   29  Aisha Sevilleja and Shirley   Predictors of Health-
                                 Kerchaten              Related Fitness Among
                                                        First-Year College
                                                        Students
             4   11.30 - 11.45   40  Made Agus Wijaya, Putu   Discipline of Fitness
                                 Panca Adi and Kadek Yogi   Members in the
                                 Parta Lesmana          Adaptation of New Habits
                                                        in Buleleng Regency
             5   11.45 - 12.00   42  Damiati and Made Suriani   Nutritional And
                                                        Organoleptic Quality of
                                                        Tempe Now With The
                                                        Addition Of Natural
                                                        Dyeing Ingredients
             6   12.00 - 12.15   45  I Putu Panca Adi, Wahjoedi,  The Effectiveness of
                                             11]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[and Damiati            Blended Training in The
                                                        Development of Rock
                                                        Climbing Athletes In
                                                        Buleleng Regency In
                                                        2021
             7   12.15 - 12.30   11  I Ketut Yoda, I.P. Adi   Analysis of Needs for The
                                 Wibowo and Ria Tri Harini   Development of Physical
                                 Dwi Rusiawati, Ketut   Education Learning Model
                                 Chandra Adinata Kusuma,   in Elementary School
                                 Gede Doddy Tisna M.S.   Based On Traditional
                                                        Game
             8   12.30 - 12.45   55  Ronica de Leon     Numerical Simulation and
                                                        Sensitivity Analysis of
                                                        Dengue Model with
                                                        Vector Control
             9   12.45 – 13.00   60  Herve E. Orpilla, and Daniel  Community Management
                                 A. Neri                Information Systems for
                                                        the Municipality of
                                                        Bacnotan
            10  13.00 – 13.15   51  I Gede Astra Wesnawa and   Social Determination of
                                 Putu Indra Christiawan   Coastal Communities in
                                                        Utilizing Coastal
                                                        Resources
            11  13.15 – 13.30   66  A.A. Ngurah Yudha   Plausible Eclecticism: A
                                 Mahardika and Ni Putu   Joint Venture of Methods
                                 Astiti Pratiwi         And Post-method
                                                        Pedagogy
                                     Parallel Session 2
                                     Breakout Room F
                              Session Chair : M. Rudi Irwansyah
            No      Time     ID          Author                 Title

             1   10.45 - 11.00   6   Dewi Oktofa Rachmawati   Physical Parameters of
                                 and Iwan Suswandi      Used Cooking Oil
                                                        Clearance Quality Based
                                                        on Active Charcoal
                                                        Temperature
             2   11.00 - 11.15   16  I Gede Aris Gunadi, Dewi   Simulation-Prediction
                                 Oktofa Rahmawati, Aldi   Model of Soil Erosion in
                                 Prayoga, Muhammad      Lake Buyan

                                             12]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Fhauzan
             3   11.15 - 11.30   3   Gst Ayu Mahayukti and   Validity and Practicality of
                                 Putu Kartika Dewi      Problem-Based Integral
                                                        Calculus Teaching
                                                        Materials Assisted with
                                                        Mathematical Software
             4   11.30 - 11.45   7   Made Vivi Oviantari, I Ketut   Contribution of Tropical
                                 Sudiana, I Dewa Ketut   Fruit Plants and Soil
                                 Sastrawidana,I Agung   Properties To The
                                 Ngurah Suryaputra, and I   Potential Of Carbon
                                 Made Gunamantha        Squastration In Open
                                                        Land Utilization For Mixed
                                                        Plantations
             5   11.45 - 12.00   56  Karen Ballada, Mark Kevin   Diversity of Trees and
                                 Lopez, and Jaures Nalica   Shrubs in DMMMSU-
                                                        NLUC Forest
             6   12.00 - 12.15   15  Ni Ketut Rapi, Putu   The Effect of Self-
                                 Widiarini and I Wayan   Assessment with Inquiry
                                 Suastra                Learning Model to Self-
                                                        Efficacy and Physics
                                                        Learning Outcomes
             7   12.15 - 12.30   59  Mark Kevin Lopez, and   Isolation, Purification and
                                 Francis Ruel Castillo   Molecular Identification of
                                                        Microfungi from the
                                                        Landfill Site of Bangar, La
                                                        Union, Philippines
             8   12.30 – 12.45   62  Excel V. Cabrera, Jessie B.   Data Encryption Based on
                                 Vallecera, Maricel O. Pre,   ERC5 Algorithm Ver. 2.0
                                 Krizia Ann E. Ramirez   for Self - Checkout Kiosk
             9   12.45 – 13.00   65  Celso Jucutan      Potential of Vetiver
                                                        (Vetiveria zizanioides) on
                                                        Leachate Treatment
            10  13.00 – 13.15   44  Ni Putu Novita Puspa Dewi   Big Data for Indonesian
                                 and I Putu Budhi Darma   Marine Fisheries: A
                                 Purwanta               preliminary research plan
            11  13.15 – 13.30   68  Raymund Sanchez, Delia V   Extraction of Dye from
                                 Lopez and Flory M Libunao   Weeds and Dyeing of Silk
                                                        Yarn Degummed with
                                                        Wood Ash


                                             13]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[INDEX

                  Improve  immunity  by  doing  Yoga  Asanas  as  Spiritual   20
                  Healing  : A Review

                  Psychometric  Properties  of  the  Indonesian  Version   21
                  Students Well-Being Scale: A Confirmatory Factor Analysis
                  and Concurrent Validity

                  Validity and Practicality of Problem-Based Integral Calculus   22
                  Teaching Materials Assisted with Mathematical Software

                  Development  of  Textbooks  Based  on  Research  in  the   23
                  Perspective of Education and Tourism Development in the
                  Bukit Kangin Forest, Tenganan Pegringsingan

                  How  is  The  Learning  Process  and  Assessment  in  E-  24
                  Learning  According  to  Japanese  High  School/Vocational
                  High School Teachers in Bali

                  Physical  Parameters  of  Used  Cooking  Oil  Clearance   25
                  Quality Based on Active Charcoal Temperature

                  Contribution of Tropical Fruit Plants and Soil Properties to   26
                  The  Potential  of  Carbon  Squastration  in  Open  Land
                  Utilization For Mixed Plantations

                  The Practicality of D-MENBOLAInteractive Learning Media   27
                  in Higher Education

                  Analysis  of  Needs  for  the  Development  of  Physical   28
                  Education Learning Model in Elementary School Based on
                  Traditional Game

                  The Influence of Social Attitude on Cognitive Competence   29
                  and Practices in Learning Governance Courses on Family
                  Welfare Education Students

                  Relationship  Between  Discussion  Activity  and  Try-Out  on   30
                  Learning Outcomes of Medical Students

                                             14]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Development  of  Mobile  Based  Application  for  Balinese   31
                  Lontar Image Transliteration

                  The Effect of Self-Assessment with Inquiry Learning Model   32
                  to Self-Efficacy and Physics Learning Outcomes

                  Simulation-Prediction Model of Soil Erosion in Lake Buyan   33

                  The Development of a Trilingual Dictionary for Elementary   34
                  Students

                  The Stiffness of Virus Shell: Influenza Lipid Shell      35

                  The  Development  of  an  Android-Based  Kata  Kolok  Sign   36
                  Language Dictionary

                  Analysis of The Maintain of Bali Traditional Games Through   37
                  Photos And Videos of GAMES to Improve Digital Literacy

                  Exploring Student Academic Procrastination Based on Time   38
                  Management, Social Support and Self-Efficacy

                  Sustainable Forests in Bali: Factors That Affect It      39
                  (Semi Log Model Analysis)

                  The Essays of Fourth Grade Elementary School Students:   40
                  A Syntactic Study Based on Character Education Values

                  Self-Managed Learning in Online Learning                 41

                  How is the Instructional Video Development Process With   42
                  Dynamic Drawing Principles?

                  Implementation  of  Project-Based  E-Learning  in  Courses   43
                  Description Statistics During Covid-19

                  A  Development  of  Chinese  and  Japanese  Culinary     44
                  Teaching Materials in Asia Culinary Courses

                  The  Implementation  of  Fussion  Food  Teaching  Materials   45
                  Based  on  Local  Bali  Food  in  Vocational  High  School

                                             15]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Students in Culinary Expertise

                  Predictors  of  Health-Related  Fitness  Among  First-Year   46
                  College Students

                  Empowerment  of  Balinese  Local  Wisdom  and  Important   47
                  Elements of Community Life As Learning Sourcesin of IPS
                  SMP/MTs. in Buleleng Regency

                  TBLA-Based  Reflective  Learning  Model  Analysis  is    48
                  Effective  as  a  Technique  for  Strengthening  Students’
                  Pattern of Learning

                  Enhancing  EFL  Students’  Speaking  Competency  Through   49
                  Animated Learning Video

                  T Boosting The Quality of EFL Class through              50
                  HOTS-based English Activity Book:
                  Upgrading Independent Active Class during Pandemic

                  A Need Analysis in English Material for XI Grade of Beauty   51
                  Program at SMK N 2 Singaraja

                  Developing  Students’  Worksheet  HOTS-Based  English    52
                  Learning for Fourth Grade Students of Elementary School

                  Mobile  Assisted  Language  Learning  in  Distance  Learning:   53
                  Learning Process and Students’ Perception

                  Developing  a  Student  Management  Model  Based  on     54
                  Balinese Local Wisdom

                  Readability  of  English  Teacher  Assessment  Literacy   55
                  Instrument in Indonesian Context

                  Discipline  of  Fitnes  Members  in  the    Adaptation  of  New   56
                  Habits in Buleleng Regency

                  Identification  of  Individual  Intolerance  Behavior  Trends   57
                  Through Thematic Apperception Test (TAT) Analysis

                                             16]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Nutritional and Organoleptic Quality of Tempe Now With the   58
                  Addition of Natural Dyeing Ingredients

                  Development of Tourism Master Plan in Panji Anom Village,   59
                  Sukasada District, Buleleng Regency

                  Big Data for Indonesian Marine Fisheries                 60
                  a Preliminary Research Plan

                  The Effectiveness of Blended Training in The Development   61
                  of Rock Climbing Athletes in Buleleng Regency In 2021

                  Home Care Service Application for Patients               62

                  Interaction  Patterns  of  SMA/SMK  Students  in  Buleleng   63
                  Regency  Based  on  Learning  Styles  in  Online  Learning
                  Using LMS and Social Media

                  Analysis  and  Simulation  of  Current  Zero  Crossing  Time   64
                  Interval Under Different Loads

                  The  Implementation  of  Tri  Hita  Karana  Culture-Based   65
                  Character  Education  at  Pasraman  Budi  Pekerti,  Kemenuh
                  Village, Bali

                  Forms  of  Rural  Tourism  and  Creative  Economy        66
                  Development

                  Social  Determination  of  Coastal  Communities  in  Utilizing   67
                  Coastal Resources

                  Analysis   of   Archives   Management   at   Universitas   68
                  Pendidikan Ganesha

                  The  Representation  of  Character  Education  in  the   69
                  Characterization  of  Lily  Owens  in  Sue  Monk  Kidd’s  The
                  Secret Life of Bees (2001)

                  Why  Students  Should  Like  to  Have  Severus  Snape  As  a   70
                  Teacher?


                                             17]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Web-Based  System  for  Bali  Tourism  Sentiment  Analysis   71
                  during  The  Covid-19  Pandemic  using  Django  Web
                  Framework and Naive Bayes Method

                  Numerical  Simulation  and  Sensitivity  Analysis  of  Dengue   72
                  Model with Vector Control

                  Diversity of Trees and Shrubs in DMMMSU-NLUC Forest      73

                  Content  Analysis  of  the  K  to  12  World  History  Teaching   74
                  Guides in terms of Teaching Approaches

                  Narrativizing  Student  Teachers’  Experiences  of  Teaching   75
                  English Abroad

                  Isolation,  Purification  and  Molecular  Identification  of   76
                  Microfungi  from  the  Landfill  Site  of  Bangar,  La  Union,
                  Philippines

                  Community  Management  Information  Systems  for  the    77
                  Municipality of Bacnotan
                  Determining  a  Vigorous  Beehive  Location  thru  Computer   78
                  Vision Technology

                  Data Encryption Based on ERC5 Algorithm Ver. 2.0 for     79
                  Self-Checkout Kiosk

                  Congruence  Properties  of  the  Sum  of  Positive  Powers  of   80
                  two Mersenne Primes

                  Technology  and  Livelihood  Education  Program  of      81
                  Dmmmsu: Analysis and Enhancement

                  Potential  of  Vetiver  (Vetiveria  zizanioides)  on  Leachate   82
                  Treatment

                  Plausible  Eclecticism:  A  Joint  Venture  Of  Methods  And   83
                  Post-Method Pedagogy




                                             18]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Understanding  the  Pedagogical  Dilemma  Using  the  KAP   84
                  (Knowledge,  Attitude  and  Practice)  Approach:  “What  Will
                  You Use?”“What Will You Use?”

                  Extraction  of  Dye  from  Weeds  and  Dyeing  of  Silk  Yarn   85
                  Degummed with Wood Ash

                  English  Grammar  Proficiency  of  English  Major  College   86
                  Students in the Philippines












































                                             19]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Improve immunity by doing Yoga Asanas as Spiritual Healing  : A
                                          Review

                Made Kurnia Widiastuti Giri  I Wayan Muderawan  Komang Hendra Setiawan  ,
                                    1,*
                                                                          3
                                                     2,
                              Ketut Indra Purnomo Putu Arya Nugraha  5
                                             4,

               1,3,4,5 Faculty Of Medicine, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja Bali, Indonesia
               2  Faculty of Mathematics and Natural Sciences, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja Bali,
               Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: kurnia.widiastuti@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               Today, citizens of the world are faced with enormous problems in various aspects of human
               life  due  to  the  problem  of  the  COVID-19  pandemic.  The  COVID-19  pandemic  has  had  a
               negative  impact  on  all  sectors  of  Indonesian  people's  lives.  One  of  the  sectors  that  was
               significantly affected was the health sector. The main factor that can prevent the transmission
               of the spread of COVID-19 that can hurt our bodies is by implementing a clean and healthy
               lifestyle and keeping our immune system stable and good. One way to maintain physical and
               mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic is to do spiritual healing which can have an
               impact in the form of a balanced mindset, mental resilience, and having a strong immune
               system. One example of the application of spiritual healing is yoga. There are various types of
               yoga and one of them is yoga asanas. By doing yoga asanas, one can rejuvenate the body's
               skeletal framework, increase appetite, and this technique also helps in treating all digestive
               organs and can reduce mental tension or stress that can reduce the body's immune power
               (immunity)  in  dealing  with  microbes  that  interfere  with  our  body.  The  movements  in  yoga
               asanas are Tadasana (Mountain Pose), Vrikshasana (Tree Pose), Adho Mukho Svanasana
               (Downward Dog Pose), Trikonasana (Triangle Pose), Kursiasana (Chair Pose), Naukasana
               (Boat Pose), Bhujangasana (Cobra Pose), Paschimottanasana (Forward Hunchback Pose),
               Balasana (Child Pose) and Sukhasana (Happy Pose). Yoga practice can activate the immune
               system by activating the thymus gland, which is located in the area between the heart and the
               breastbone. The thymus gland produces T-Cells which are a heterogeneous group of cells
               important  in  protecting  the  body  against  invasion  by  foreign  organisms.  With  the  various
               benefits described, the concept of spiritual healing, especially the application of yoga asanas,
               is very suitable to be applied during the COVID-19 pandemic in order to improve body and
               mental conditions for the better which will have an impact on increasing the body's immunity
               in preventing the entry of viruses or other antigens that can cause infection.

               Keywords: COVID-19 pandemic, Body immunity, Physical and mental health, Spiritual
               healing, Yoga asanas.




                                                20]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Psychometric Properties of the Indonesian Version Students
                    Well-Being Scale: A Confirmatory Factor Analysis and
                                     Concurrent Validity

                 Kadek Suranata ,Itsar Bolo Rangka , I Putu Agus Apriliana , Ifdil , Wayan Eka
                                            2
                                                             3
                                                                 4
                             1,*
                                  Paramartha , I Ketut Dharsana 6
                                           5

               1,3,5,6  Guidance and Counseling Department, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia
               2  Guidance and Counseling Department, Universitas Indraprasta PGRI, Jakarta, Indonesia
               4 Guidance and Counseling Department, Universitas Negeri Padang, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: kadek.suranata@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               This study aims at evaluating the psychometric properties the Indonesian version of
               the student well-being scale. This research involved 444 high school students in Bali
               Province,  Indonesia  during  the  period  from  April  to  May  2019.  The  original
               psychometric well-being (SWB) scale was first published by Ryff and Keyes in 1995
               and the existing Indonesian model is a direct adaptation of this theoretical model.
               The objectives of this research paper were to derive a simplified construction of the
               Indonesian  model,  such  that  its  administration  and  usefulness  could  be  more
               broadly applied by limited educational resources. Through a series of iterations in
               the CFA analysis procedure, 15 items from the six-dimension SWB scale have been
               generated.  Concurrent  validity  confirms  by  high  correlation  by  Person  Product
               moment of the SWB scale with the HPLP II. Indeed, this study implies that an SWB
               scale  with  six  dimensions  and  15-items  is  an  instrument  with  the  potential  to
               accurately measure the psychological well-being of Indonesian students.

               Keywords: Student mental health, Assessment in counseling, CFA.












                                                21]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Validity and Practicality of Problem-Based Integral Calculus
                   Teaching Materials Assisted with Mathematical Software

                               Gst Ayu Mahayukti * Putu Kartika Dewi 2
                                             1,

               1 Prodi Pendidikan Matematika, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia
               2 Prodi Matematika, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: gustiayumahayukti@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               This study aims to develop Integral Calculus teaching materials to improve students'
               communication skills and positive character. The teaching materials developed are
               problem-based with the help of mathematical software. The model used refers to the
               Plomp model. Data on the validity of teaching materials were collected using expert
               evaluation  questionnaires,  practicality  data  on  teaching  materials  were  collected
               using  student  response  questionnaires  given  to  students  for  the  2020/2021
               academic  year,  and  lecturer  responses.  Data  were  analyzed  by  descriptive
               statistics. The results showed that the teaching materials developed had met the
               valid and practical criteria. Based on the results of the questionnaire, the validity and
               practicality  of  teaching  materials  need  to  be  optimized  again  in  the  content,
               assessment and answer key sections so that they can develop student creativity,
               especially in communication skills and positive character.

               Keywords: Communication skills, Positive character, Problem-based.


















                                                22]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Development of Textbooks Based on Research in the
                Perspective of Education and Tourism Development in the Bukit
                           Kangin Forest, Tenganan Pegringsingan

                               Nyoman Wijana  Sanusi Mulyadiharja 2*
                                           1,*

               1,2 Biology Education Study Program, Faculty of Mathematics and Natural Sciences, Universitas
                 Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: nyoman.wijana@undiksha.ac.id, sanusi.mulyadiharja@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               Research has been carried out on the forest vegetation of Bukit Kangin and the
               results of the research are arranged in the form of a textbook. This book is designed
               to  be  used  in  the  perspective  of  education  and  forest  tourism  development.  The
               purpose  of  this  study  was  to  determine  the  feasibility  and  practicality  of  using
               textbooks  as  teaching  materials  in  the  educational  perspective  of  the  Biology
               Education study program, FMIPA Undiksha and the perspective of developing forest
               tourism  in  the  Tenganan  Pegringsingan  traditional  village.  The  population  of  this
               study were (1) Lecturers of the Biology Education Study Program, Department of
               Marine  Biology  and  Fisheries,  FMIPA  Undiksha,  students,  Lecturers  of  design
               experts  and  the  Tourism  Awareness  Group  of  the  Tenganan  Pegringsingan
               traditional village. The research sample amounted to 36 people. The location of the
               textbook  product  test  was  carried  out  in  the  classroom  and  in  the  Bukit  Kangin
               forest, Tenganan Pegringsingan traditional village. The development of this textbook
               is designed to follow the ADDIE development model. The data collection method in
               this  study  used  interviews,  questionnaires,  and  literature  studies.  Data  were
               analyzed descriptively quantitatively. The results showed that the book compiled as
               teaching  materials  used  in  the  educational  perspective  of  the  Biology  Education
               study program, FMIPA Undiksha and the perspective of developing forest tourism in
               the  Tenganan  Pegringsingan  traditional  village  had  very  good  feasibility  and
               practicality values.

               Keywords: Textbooks, Research-based, Education, Forest tourism.









                                                23]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[How is The Learning Process and Assessment in E-Learning
                  According to Japanese High School/Vocational High School
                                      Teachers in Bali

                             Desak Made Sri Mardani  I Wayan Sadyana 2
                                               1,*

               1,2 Department of Foreign Language, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: desak.mardani@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               E-learning  used  during  this  pandemic  is  something  new  for  Japanese  high
               school/vocational teachers in Bali, where previous learning was done face-to-face.
               This  causes  the  teacher's  lack  of  experience  in  implementing  e-learning.  The
               teacher's lack of experience certainly has an influence on the learning process, as
               well as the assessment made by the teacher. For this reason, it is necessary to
               conduct research related to the learning process and assessment in e-learning from
               the teacher's perspective. This study uses a descriptive quantitative approach. The
               questionnaire  data  of  the  research  was  analyzed  using  a  t-test,  and  analysis  of
               variance  (ANOVA).  A  purposive  online  survey  was  participated  by  117  high
               school/vocational Japanese language teachers in Bali conducted from October to
               December  2020.  There  are  no  significant  differences  between  male  and  female
               teachers, between teachers with bachelor and master levels, and between teachers
               with different teaching periods. This can also be seen in the teacher's perspective
               on  the  assessments  carried  out  during  e-learning,  between  female  and  male
               teachers, and between teachers at the bachelor and master levels. However, from
               the perspective of the assessment between teachers who have different years of
               teaching  experience,  several  significant  differences  were  found.  During  the
               implementation  of  e-learning,  teachers  encountered  problems  in  the  learning
               process and assessment, which stemmed from the lack of facilities, lack of student
               readiness, and lack of teaching experience in planning assessments that we're able
               to show students' abilities objectively.

               Keywords: Purposive online survey, Learning process, Assessment.








                                                24]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Physical Parameters of Used Cooking Oil Clearance Quality
                           Based on Active Charcoal Temperature

                              Dewi Oktofa Rachmawati  Iwan Suswandi 2
                                                1*,

               1,2 Physics Education Study Program, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: dewioktofa.r@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               Oil purification is a common method used by the community to reuse used cooking
               oil. The use of various adsorbents that are rampantly carried out aimed at obtaining
               the  quality  of  used  cooking  oil  that  is  safe  for  consumption.  However,  in  the
               adsorption process, not all adsorbents can restore the quality of cooking oil. Active
               charcoal is one of the effective adsorbents used for the purification process. Heating
               active  charcoal  is  carried  out  to  activate  the  adsorbent  in  order  to  increase  the
               adsorption  capacity  of  the  contaminants  and  water  content  in  the  oil.  Physical
               parameter  of  used  cooking  oil  purification  quality  based  on  active  charcoal
               temperature was decribed in this study. Clarified used cooking oil was cooking oil
               with 3 times of discontinuous use. The temperature of the active charcoal adsorbent
               varied, namely 27oC, 40oC, 50oC, 70oC, and 90oC. The color test was carried out
               organoleptically and analyzed using the senses of the eye. Density test used the
               principle  of  mass  to  volume  ratio.  The  oven  method  with  the  principle  of  losing
               weight at 1050C was used to test the moisture content. The refraction index test
               used  the  principle  of  parallel  plan  glass  refraction.  All  data  were  analyzed
               descriptively referring to the quality standard of cooking oil, namely SNI number:
               3741  of  2013.  Used  cooking  oil  purified  with  active  charcoal  adsorbent  at  a
               temperature  of  90o  C  has  a  golden  yellow  color  with  oil  density  value  of
               0.8763±0.0336 gram/cm3, the refraction index of the oil 1.447±0.029, water content
               in oil 0.087±0.171 %.

               Keywords: Used cooking oil, Physical parameters, Active charcoal.










                                                25]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Contribution of Tropical Fruit Plants and Soil Properties to The
                 Potential of Carbon Squastration in Open Land Utilization For
                                     Mixed Plantations

                           M V Oviantari , I K Sudiana , I D W K Sastrawidana ,
                                                                3
                                    1
                                              2
                               I A N G Suryaputra , I M Gunamantha *
                                                           5
                                             4

               1,2,3,4,5 Jurusan Kimia, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: md_gunamantha@yahoo.com


                                           Abstract
               This study is planned to assess the future carbon storage potential of mixed garden
               systems for campus open spaces through an estimation approach by assessing 10
               tropical  fruit  plants  developed  on  community  plantations  around  Buleleng  district.
               Three trees were selected for each type. Each tree was measured for its physical
               dimensions including diameter at breast height (DBH) and tree height. Soil carbon
               was  also  using  the  Walkley–Black  method  in  a  subset  of  plots.  The  relationship
               between soil chemical properties and soil SOC potential was also analyzed. It was
               found that the potential carbon stock of trees ranged from 8 to 4915 Gg ha-1, with
               the smallest average potential value being soursop trees and the largest average
               value  indicated  by  durian  trees.  The  average  soil  carbon  stock  in  the  observed
               campus area is 440 Gg ha-1. If the combination of four tropical fruit crops with the
               highest  carbon  storage  potential  (duria,  jackfruit,  rambutan,  and  sapodilla)  is
               selected and planted proportionally, it will provide a carbon storage potential of 2101
               Gg  ha-1  in  trees.  This  study  also  found  the  relationship  between  physical  and
               chemical  properties  of  soil  with  SOC.  The  finer  particles  affect  SOC.  All  soil
               chemical properties which were negatively correlated with SOC were also negatively
               correlated with CEC. Except for the N-total which is strongly positively correlated. N-
               total  with  other  soil  chemical  properties  is  also  negatively  correlated.  The  low
               content of N-total and CEC of the soil resulted in the low SOC of the soil in the study
               area.

               Keywords: Carbon squastration, Soil, Tropical fruit plants.







                                                26]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[The Practicality of D-MENBOLA
                        Interactive Learning Media In Higher Education

               Ketut Chandra Adinata Kusuma  I Wayan Artanayasa  Adrianus I Wayan Ilia Yuda
                                      1,*
                                                       2,
                                          Sukmana 3

               1,2,3 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: chandra.adinata@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The use of interactive learning media is a demand in the distance learning period.
               The learning media developed must be easily used by students to achieve learning
               objectives. The purpose of this study is to describe the practicality of D-MENBOLA,
               a  football  learning  media  for  sports  coaching  education  students.  This  research
               includes  development  research  using  the  ADDIE  model  (Analysis,  Design,
               Development,  Implementation,  Evaluation).  The  practicality  data  collection
               technique uses a practicality test questionnaire filled out by 10 students. The data
               on  the  completed  practicality  test  questionnaire  instrument  was  then  analysed
               quantitatively.  Based  on  the  results  of  the  practicality  test,  it  is  known  that  the
               developed  D-MENBOLA  belongs  to  the  very  practical  category  with  an  average
               percentage  score  of  88.33%.  So,  it  can  be  concluded  that  D-MENBOLA  as  a
               practical learning media is used by students. It is hoped that further research can
               reveal the effectiveness of the use of D-MENBOLA on student learning outcomes.

               Keywords: D-MENBOLA, Interactive Learning Media, The Practicality.
















                                                27]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[Analysis of Needs for the Development of Physical Education
               Learning Model in Elementary School Based on Traditional Game

                  I Ketut Yoda  I.P. Adi Wibowo Ria Tri Harini Dwi Rusiawati Ketut Chandra
                                        2,
                                                              3,
                           1,*
                              Adinata Kusuma Gede Doddy Tisna M.S 5
                                          4,

               1,2,3,4,5 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: yodaketut@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The aim of this research is to obtain information and data related to the analysis of
               the  need  for  the  development  of  physical  education  and  health  learning  model
               based on traditional game in elementary schools. The population of this study were
               50  elementary  schools  in  Buleleng  District  consisting  of  13  private  elementary
               schools  and  37  public  elementary  schools.  Determination  of  the  sample  is
               determined randomly and selected proportionally in each elementary school. Each
               of these schools has heterogeneity, environment, and customs that are different, so
               these schools are also considered in determining the research sample. Data were
               collected  using  participatory  observation  methods,  documentation  studies,
               interviews, FGDs, and questionnaires (questionnaires. The results of the study are
               based  on  the  competencies  expected  from  the  implementation  of  learning
               (standardized  processes)  of  the  elementary  school  Physical  Education  (PE)
               curriculum,  student  characteristics,  and  the  opinions  of  elementary  school  PE
               teachers, so a learning model for SD PJOK based on traditional Balinese games is
               needed  to  improve  students'  physical  fitness,  manipulation  Motor  Skill  and
               Character of Elementary School students.

               Keywords: Learning models, Physical education, Traditional games.














                                                28]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[The Influence of Social Attitude on Cognitive Competence and
                 Practices in Learning Governance Courses on Family Welfare
                                     Education Students

                             Luh Masdarini ,  Ida Ayu Putu Hemy Ekayani 2*
                                       1 *

               1,2 Jurusan Teknologi Industri, Fakultas Teknik dan Kejuruan, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja,
               Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: masdarini@undiksha.ac.id , hemy.ekayani@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The aims of this study were 1) to determine the effect of social attitudes on cognitive
               competence in the culinary arts course for family welfare education students, 2) to
               determine the effect of social attitudes on practical competence in the culinary arts
               course to family welfare education students, 3) to determine the interaction of social
               attitudes. on cognitive competence and practical competence in the culinary arts
               course for family welfare education students. The method used to collect data is a
               questionnaire method, knowledge test, and observation with instruments in the form
               of a closed statement questionnaire to collect data on social attitudes, multiple coice
               knowledge  test  to  obtain  data  on  cognitive  competence  in  the  form  of  student
               understanding in the culinary arts course, and an observation rubric. to obtain data
               on  the  practical  competence  of  students  in  the  culinary  arts  course.  The  results
               showed  that  1)  different  competencies  were  not  influenced  by  different  social
               attitudes in the Dishes course, 2) the level of student social attitudes did not affect
               students' cognitive competence and practice, meaning that students from various
               levels  of  social  attitudes,  both  high  and  medium  social  attitudes.  or  low  have
               relatively balanced cognitive and practical competencies in the culinary arts course,
               3)  there  is  no  significant  interaction  between  students'  social  attitudes  towards
               competence in the culinary arts course. Students who have high, medium and low
               social attitudes have relatively the same cognitive and practical competencies.

               Keywords: Social attitude, Cognitive competence, Practical competence, Cuisine.









                                                29]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Relationship Between Discussion Activity and Try-Out on
                           Learning Outcomes of Medical Students

                             Adnyana Putra , Made Kurnia Widiastuti Giri 2
                                        1*

               1,2 Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: adnyanaputra@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               This study aimed to examine the relationship between the level of discussion activity
               and the results of try-out with learning outcomes in medical students. The research
               design used was quantitative observational cross-sectional research. The subjects
               were students in semester 1, 3, and 5 from Study Program of Medicine Universitas
               Pendidikan Ganesha Academic Year 2021/2022. Level of discussion activity was
               assessed  by  the  discussion  score  determined  by  number  of  responses  and
               questions asked. Try-out variable was taken from the results of try-out carried out by
               student’s  organization.  Learning  outcomes  was  obtained  from  final  exam  score.
               Data were analysed descriptively. Next step data of learning outcomes on status of
               try-out  (took  or  didn’t  take)  were  compared.  On  final  analysis  correlation  and
               regression analysis were determined. About 56 out of 151 subjects were excluded
               from  final  step  of  analysis  because  they  didn’t  take  try-out  program.  The  results
               showed  that  the  discussion  score  and  try-out  score  have  an  effect  of  20.1%
               (p<0.001)  on  learning  outcomes.  Other  results  also  showed  that  the  final  exam
               scores of students who took the try-out were higher than the students who did not
               take  the  try-out  (average  score=76.37,  SD=13.28  vs  average  score=68.78,
               SD=16.33;  p<0.01).  It  can  be  concluded  that  discussion  process  and  try-out
               correlate with learning outcomes.

               Keywords: Discussion, Try-out, Learning outcomes, Medical student.













                                                30]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[Development of Mobile Based Application for Balinese Lontar
                                    Image Transliteration

                Made Windu Antara Kesiman  Kadek Teguh Dermawan , Gede Aditra Pradnyana 3
                                                         2
                                     1,*

               1,2,3 Virtual, Vision, Image, and Pattern Research Group, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali,
               Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: antara.kesiman@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               AKSALont is an application that can automatically transliterate the digital image of
               Lontar Bali into text data format in the Latin alphabet. Seeing the wider needs of the
               AKSALont application, it was deemed necessary to develop a mobile application
               version of Akasalont that remains integrated with the main web-based application.
               This paper presents the detail development process of mobile based application of
               AKSALont. Three main development phases are presented. Software design phase
               consists  of  software  architecture  design  and  software  interface  design.  Software
               implementation  modules  for  AKSALont  mobile  application  consists  of  three  sub
               modules,  namely  image  cropping  module,  machine  interconnection  module,  and
               mobile  application  interface  module.  Several  black  box  testing  scenarios  were
               performed  to  test  the  software.  Results  show  that  the  mobile  based  interface  of
               AKSALont is successfully integrated in an interconnection with the main web server
               and machine of AKSALont.

               Keywords: Mobile based application, Balinese lontar, Image, Transliteration.


















                                                31]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[The Effect of Self-Assessment with Inquiry Learning Model to
                        Self-Efficacy and Physics Learning Outcomes

                            Ni Ketut Rapi  Putu Widiarini  I Wayan Suastra 3
                                      1,*
                                                  2,

               123 Prodi Pendidikan Fisika, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: ketutrapi658@gmail.com


                                           Abstract
               The main aim of this study was to determine the differences in self-efficacy and
               physics  learning  outcomes  between  students  who  were  facilitated  by  self-
               assessment  with  inquiry  learning  model  and  students  who  were  facilitated  by
               conventional assessments. This study used a posttest only non-equivalent control
               group  design.  The  sample  was  16  students  of  the  second  semester  of  physics
               education study program, FMIPA Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha that was divided
               into two equivalent groups determined by random. The used instruments were self-
               efficacy  questionnaire  and  physics  learning  outcome  test  in  the  essay  form.  The
               reliability of the self-efficacy questionnaire and the physics learning outcome test
               were 0.81 and 0.76, respectively. The data were analyzed using descriptive and
               multivariate analysis. The results showed that: (1) the average value of self-efficacy
               in  the  experimental  group  was  82.6  with  a  standard  deviation  of  6.1  in  the  high
               category and 73.9 in the control group with a standard deviation of 3.4 in the high
               category. (2) the average value of physics learning outcomes in the experimental
               group is 80.0 with a standard deviation of 10.5 in the high category and the control
               group is 65.2 with a standard deviation of 12.0 in the moderate category; and (3)
               there  are  differences  in  self-efficacy  and  physics  learning  outcomes  between
               students  who  are  facilitated  by  self-assessment  with  inquiry  learning  model  and
               those  facilitated  by  conventional  assessments.  This  means  that  self-assessment
               with  inquiry  learning  model  has  a  better  influence  on  the  achievement  of  self-
               efficacy and student physics learning outcomes.

               Keywords: Inquiry, Self-assessment, Self-efficacy, Physics learning outcomes.









                                                32]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[Simulation-Prediction Model of Soil Erosion in Lake Buyan

                  I Gede Aris Gunadi  Dewi Oktofa Rachmawati  Aldi Prayoga  Muhammad
                                1,*
                                                     2,
                                                               3,
                                          Fhauzan 4

               1 Programe  study  Magister  Computer  Science/Programe  Study  Physiscs  Education,  Universitas
               Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia
               2 ,3 Programe Study Physiscs Education, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia
               4 Programe  study  Magister  Computer  Science,  Universitas  Pendidikan  Ganesha,  Singaraja,  Bali,
               Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: igedearisgunadi@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The existence of the lake is very important for the Balinese people, as a source of
               drinking water, as well as in the spiritual aspects of Hindu religion. One of the lakes
               on the island of Bali is Lake Buyan. Geographically, it is located in Pancasari village,
               Sukasada district, Buleleng, Bali.  The Bali Provincial Public Works Department '
               Data  shows  that  in  the  last  15  years  from  1999  to  2015,  there  is  an  increasing
               decrease in the area of the lake. In 1999 the area of the lake was recorded at 439
               Ha and shrunk in 2015 to 376 Ha.  One of the factors that affect the area of the lake
               is the occurrence of soil erosion. In this study, a simulation model was developed to
               predict landslide/soil erosion conditions in Lake Buyan. This avalanche simulation
               model is based on the USLE (Universal Soil Loss Equation) formula. It is stated that
               erosion is influenced by soil erobility, rain erosivity, steepness of slopes, tillage, and
               soil  conversion.  Based  on  the  developed  simulation  model,  it  is  shown  that  the
               biggest influence that affects the landslide in Buyan Lake is rain erosivity. Rainfall
               predictions  based  on  rainfall  data  for  the  last  10  years  show  that  the  rainfall  is
               getting smaller. On the one hand, it will bring the advantage that the quantity of
               landslide erosion in the next few decades will be smaller. Based on the simulation
               model, predictions show that in 2020, 2030, 2040, and 2050 the amount of erosion
               is 116.5 tons, 74.23 tons, 18.62 tons, and 7.5 tons. On the other hand, this is very
               worrying because rain is the only source of water for Lake Buyan.

               Keywords: Lake erotion, USLE, Dynamic simulation, Buyan lake.








                                                33]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[The Development of a Trilingual Dictionary for Elementary
                                          Students

                    Ni Luh Putu Sri Adnyani , Ni Made Rai Wisudariani ,  I Nyoman Pasek
                                                         2 *
                                      1
                        Hadisaputra , Ni Komang Arie Suwastini , Putu Wiraningsih 5
                                                     4
                                 3

               1,2,3,4,5 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: rai.wisudariani@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               Elementary  schools  in  Bali  introduce  a  minimum  of  three  languages,  including
               Balinese as a local language, Indonesian as the national language, and English as a
               foreign language to students. However, the presence of a dictionary that is focused
               in  assisting  students  in  mastering  the  three  languages  is  very  limited.  Thus,  this
               study was aimed at; 1) analyzing the scope of vocabularies that must be learned by
               elementary school students, 2) developing a trilingual Balinese-Indonesian-English
               dictionary  for  elementary  school  students.  Applying  research  and  development
               design,  the  data  were  collected  through  observation,  interviews  and  document
               studies. The results revealed that there were 18 major themes of vocabularies that
               should  be  learned  in  Balinese,  Indonesian,  and  English.  Contextual  selection  of
               themes  and  vocabulary  accompanied  with  illustrations  provides  a  better
               understanding in acquiring the new vocabularies. Besides, the efforts to preserve
               local culture and maintain self-identity in globalization era can also be achieved.

               Keywords: Dictionary, Elementary students, Trilingual.
















                                                34]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[The Stiffness of Virus Shell: Influenza Lipid Shell

                    M.R. Fauzi , Nurfa Risha , Gede Aris Gunadi , Luh Putu Budi Yasmini 4*
                                      2
                                                     3
                            1

               1,2,3,4 Mathematics and Science Faculty, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali,
               Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: budi.yasmini@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               Virus  is  an  infectious  agent  with  microscopic  size,  a  protective  shell  containing
               capsomere with protein material called a capsid, and the addition shell containing fat
               called a lipid coat. The one characteristic of a virus is about the shell stiffness, so
               the virus shell can assuming as a spring. The value of stiffness of the virus shell is
               different for various viruses depending on intrinsic properties (modulus of elasticity)
               and extrinsic properties (radius and thickness of the virus shell). In this paper, we
               analyze the value of stiffness of the virus shell by analytical dan simulation. The
               analytical method is based on plate and shell theory and Michell solution. The other,
               the simulation is based on finite element analysis (FEA) method. For influenza lipid
               shell, we find that the stiffness value of the shell based on plate and shell theory is
               0.0236  !" . Based on Michell solution, the stiffness value of the shell is 0.0225  !" .
                     !#                                                   !#
               Also, the stiffness value of influenza lipid by FEA method is 0.0227 ± 0.0002   !" .
                                                                          !#
               Generally,  based  on  the  graph  that  the  stiffness  value  of  influenza  lipid  shell  by
               analytical and simulation is approaching same.

               Keywords: Virus shell, Stiffness, Michell equation, Plate & shell theory, FEA.















                                                35]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[The Development of an Android-Based Kata Kolok Sign
                                    Language Dictionary

                 Ni Luh Putu Sri Adnyani , Gede Aditra Pradnyana  Ni Made Rai Wisudariani ,
                                                     2,*
                                                                         3
                                   1
                            I Made Ardwi Pradnyana , Gede Rasben Dantes 5
                                              4

               1,2,3,4,5 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: gede.aditra@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               This study aimed at developing Kata Kolok sign language dictionary by utilizing an
               Android application. Applying Rapid Application Development (RAD) design model,
               several stages have been conducted namely business modelling, data modelling,
               process  modelling,  application  formation,  and  testing  and  turnover.  The
               development  of  this  sign  language  dictionary  application  used  the  React  Native
               framework to create mobile applications and firebase for the application backend.
               Several  main  features  were  included  in  this  sign  language  dictionary  such  as
               registration,  login,  search,  word  categories,  and  search  history.  Therefore,  the
               development of Kata Kolok sign language dictionary was expected to assist the deaf
               and hard of hearing children or referred to as kolok in learning the sign language
               through the presence of visual materials in the learning app.

               Keywords: Android-based dictionary, Kata kolok, Sign language.


















                                                36]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[Analysis of The Maintain of Bali Traditional Games Through
                                Photos And Videos of GAMES
                                 to Improve Digital Literacy

                           Made Agus Dharmadi , AA Yudha Martin Mahardika 2
                                          1

               1,2 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: agus.dharmadi@undiksha.ac.id, yudha.martin@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               This research is a follow-up study on the development of a website about traditional
               Balinese games in the previous year, because the website developed did not fully
               contain the types of games and game media in the form of photos and videos. This
               website  will  contain  information  and  traditional  Balinese  games  by  searching
               documents about traditional games in Bali which are then integrated into the form of
               text,  images  and  videos  that  will  be  published  on  the  website.  Data  collection
               techniques used are literature study and documentation studies, interviews (FGD),
               and questionnaires (questionnaires). The activity plan adopts a system development
               life cycle consisting of planning, analysis, design, implementation (build and coding),
               testing and maintenance. Based on this, it can be concluded that photo and video
               media on websites about traditional Balinese games are very much needed (95%)
               considering  that  there  is  no  single  website  that  can  display  traditional  Balinese
               games as a whole, and also in the midst of declining interest in reading through
               books and developments. increasingly modern technology in the era of industry 4.0.
               This research is expected to be useful for educators, education and sports offices,
               and the department of education and culture as well as the wider community in the
               form  of  the  availability  of  traditional  Balinese  games  in  the  form  of  websites
               equipped with photos and videos, making it easier to understand, apply, educate,
               socialize  traditions,  and  develop  them.  in  the  form  of  policy  programs  for  the
               preservation of arts and culture/traditions, especially traditional Balinese games.

               Keywords: Digital Literacy, Photo and video media, Traditional games.








                                                37]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[Exploring Student Academic Procrastination Based on Time
                        Management, Social Support and Self-Efficacy

                       M. Rudi Irwansyah , Made Ary Meitriana , Ni’matul Istiqomah
                                                     2
                                     *1
                                                                    3


               1,2 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: rudi.irwansyah@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The  purpose  of  this  study  was  to  see  how  time  management,  self-efficacy,  and
               social  support  affected  students  at  the  Faculty  of  Economics  in  Singaraja's
               academic  procrastination.  This  was  causal  research  with  a  qualitative  approach.
               This  study  consisted  of  independent  variables,  namely  time  management,  self-
               efficacy,  and  social  support,  and  dependent  variable,  namely  academic
               procrastination.  The  population  was  the  students  of  the  Faculty  of  Economics  in
               Singaraja, totaling 366 students. The sampling technique applied was proportionate
               stratified  random  sampling.  The  data  of  the  research  were  obtained  using
               questionnaires. Data analysis was conducted by applying a t-test and F-test. Based
               on the findings of the study, it was discovered that time management, self-efficacy,
               and social support all had significant negative effects on students in the Economic
               Education Study Program in Singaraja's academic procrastination.

               Keywords:  Academic  procrastination,  self-efficacy,  social  Support,  Time
               management.
















                                                38]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[Sustainable Forests in Bali: Factors That Affect It
                                 (Semi Log Model Analysis)

                                 Krisna Sanjaya Komang Arthana 2
                                            1,*

               1 Faculty of Business and Tourism Economics, Hindu Indonesia University
               2 Faculty of Economiscs and Business, Nusa Cendana University

               * Corresponding author. Email: krisnasanjaya@unhi.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               On the island of Bali, efforts to conserve forests have been around for a long time
               through the tradition of wanakerti and tumpek bubuh, namely rituals of respecting
               forests  and  plants  which  are  implicitly  an  implementation  of  environmental
               preservation  and  are  also  part  of  local  wisdom.  This  is  considered  insufficient
               considering that the condition of forest areas in Bali is experiencing distortion. This
               study  aims  to  determine  the  simultaneous  and  partial  effects  of  the  factors  that
               affect forest sustainability. By using data from the 1993-2020 period analyzed with
               the semi-log model approach, it is known that simultaneously GRDP, population,
               and  decentralization  have  a  significant  effect  on  forest  preservation  during  the
               analysis  period,  while  the  decentralization  factor  does  not  partially  affect  forest
               sustainability.  Forest  is  an  integrated  ecosystem  containing  biological  natural
               resources, dominated by trees in their natural relationship with their environment.
               Therefore, forest management must rely on three pillars, namely the local economy,
               ecology, and socio-culture which also need to be considered to achieve sustainable
               forest management and utilization.

               Keywords:  Forest  sustainability,  Gross  regional  domestic  product,  Population,
               Decentralization.














                                                39]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[The Essays of Fourth Grade Elementary School Students: A
                    Syntactic Study Based on Character Education Values

                             Ida Bagus Putrayasa Dewa Putu Ramendra 2
                                            1,*

               1,2 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: ib.putrayasa@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The  main  objectives  of  this  research  are  to  describe  (1)  sentence  types,  (2)
               sentence  unity,  and  (3)  sentence  structure  based  on  character  education  values
               found in the essays of fourth grade elementary school students in Buleleng regency.
               Data  were  collected  by  document  recording  method.  The  data  collected  were
               analyzed  descriptively  qualitatively.  The  results  showed  that:  (1)  the  types  of
               sentences contained in the essays could be divided based on (a) the number of
               clauses, there were 205 single sentences, 91 compound sentences, (b) the internal
               structure of the main clause, there were 277 sentences complete and 19 incomplete
               sentences. (2) sentence unity which is indicated by the presence of: (a) Subject (S)
               and  Predicate  (P):  277  sentences  are  clearly  categorized  with  unity  of  idea;  (b)
               without the presence of S and P, only in the form of statement 4; (c) without S: 10
               sentences, and (d) without P: 5 sentences. (3) The sentence structure, both singular
               and compound, contained in the essays is quite varied. Meanwhile, the results of
               studies  concerning  the  values  of  character  education  in  the  essays  include  (a)
               religious, (b) honest, (c) hard work, (d) love of reading, (e) care for the environment,
               (f) social care, and (g) responsibility.

               Keywords: Syntax, Character education, Essay.














                                                40]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[Self-Managed Learning in Online Learning

                       Ni’matul Istiqomah  Nur Anita Yunikawati M. Rudi Irwansyah 3
                                    1,*
                                                     2,

               1,2 Universitas Negeri Malang, Malang, Indonesia
               3 Universeitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: nimatul.istiqomah.fe@um.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               This study aims to find out the benefits of self-managed learning in online learning.
               As we know, the world is currently facing a pandemic, in which most agendas are
               delayed and must be carried out online. Like education. Education as one of the
               sectors  affected  by  the  pandemic  covid19  is  undergoing  a  significant  change.
               Starting  from  the  policy  to  the  implementation  of  learning.  In  online  learning,
               students are expected to be able to apply independent learning to support online
               learning to understand the material well. The method in this research is descriptive
               qualitative by taking data through in-depth interviews with practitioners in the field of
               Education. The benefits of independent learning are that students can manage their
               learning  time  well,  have  responsibility  for  the  material  being  studied,  are  free  to
               choose teaching materials that are appropriate to the material and interests, and
               practice to improve their critical thinking skills.

               Keywords: Self-managed learning, Online learning, Learning responsibility.



















                                                41]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[How is the Instructional Video Development Process With
                                Dynamic Drawing Principles?

                       I Gde Wawan Sudatha  Adrianus I Wayan Ilia Yuda Sukmana 2
                                       1,*

               1,2 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: igdewawans@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               Technological innovation has led to changes in the teaching and learning process.
               Advances  in  computer  technology  have  enabled  the  development  of  various
               learning environments including learning videos. The theories that underlie learning
               with  learning  videos  are  cognitive  theories.  Cognitive  learning  theory  rooted  in
               information  processing  theory  is  the  foundation  of  the  development  of  learning
               videos.  The  principle  of  dynamic  drawing  is  that  people  learn  better  from  video
               lectures showing the instructor drawing graphics as he or she teaches rather than
               referring to already drawn drawings. This research is development research. The
               ADDIE  model  includes  analysis,  design,  development,  implementation,  and
               evaluation. The process of developing learning videos with the principles of dynamic
               drawing is as follows: a) analysis, b) design, c) development, and d) evaluation.

               Keywords: ADDIE, Video, Dynamic drawing.



















                                                42]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[Implementation of Project-Based E-Learning in Courses
                            Description Statistics During Covid-19

                           I Gde Wawan Sudatha  Anak Agung Gede Agung 2
                                            1,*

               1,2 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: igdewawans@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The  rapid  advancement  of  information  and  communication  technology  (ICT)  has
               provided many changes and benefits for the world of education. During the Covid-19
               pandemic, the presence of ICT has provided enormous benefits. One of the most
               important benefits is electronic-based learning (e-learning). In line with the electronic
               learning,  there  is  also  a  change  in  the  content  of  teaching  materials,  strategies,
               media,  and  evaluation  of  learning.  The  components  were  originally  presented
               manually or in print are now presented digitally or electronically. To accommodate
               these  changes,  the  Descriptive  Statistics  course  in  the  Education  Technology
               Department was designed by utilizing ICT and adopting a project-based learning
               model.  For  this  reason,  specifically  this  research  aims  to  find  out  the  significant
               difference in descriptive statistics learning outcomes between project-based learning
               project-based e-learning and project-based non-e-learning lessons. This research
               used a pre-experimental one group pretest-posttest design. The population of this
               research is the second semester students in the Education Technology Department,
               totaling 30 people consisting of 1 class. The data in this study were collected with
               observation sheets, questionnaires, and learning outcomes tests. Data on learning
               outcomes and student character were analyzed using descriptive statistics and one-
               way analysis of variance. Based on the results of the research and discussion, it can
               be concluded that there is a significant difference in descriptive statistics learning
               outcomes  between  project-based  e-learning  and  project-based  non-e-learning
               students  in  the  Education  Technology  Department.  That  project-based  e-learning
               has  an  influence  on  descriptive  statistics  learning  outcomes  for  students  of  the
               Education Technology Department.

               Keywords: E-Learning, Learning outcomes, Project based learning.







                                                43]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[A Development of Chinese and Japanese Culinary Teaching
                              Materials in Asia Culinary Courses

                                 NW Sukerti Cok Istri  R. Marsiti  2
                                          1,*

               1,2 Study Program Education Culinary Arts Vocational, Faculty of Engineering and Vocational, Universitas
               Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: wayan.sukerti@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The development of Asian Culinary teaching materials is very urgent because based
               on the needs analysis carried out, it was found that for the last three years there
               have  been  no  updated  Asian  culinary  teaching  materials  in  the  Culinary  Arts
               Vocational Education Study Program. This will make it easier for study programs
               and students to get references in the form of sources of teaching materials that are
               truly adequate and can be used by lecturers and students. Students are given the
               opportunity to do various activities meaningful activities, such as finding, exploring,
               analyzing, and expressing their thoughts. A good learning process will be realized if
               it  is  supported  by  good  learning  resources,  learning  resources  that  can  facilitate
               student-centered  learning  activities  and  are  able  to  bridge  the  gap  between  the
               material  and  its  context  in  everyday  life.  Japan  that  has  obtained  studies  from
               experts, both in terms of material or content and in terms of learning design. This
               research is development research with ADDIE model. The instrument that is used is
               the  questionnaire.  Data  were  analyzed  by  descriptive  analysis  technique
               quantitative.  The  results  of  the  content  expert  test  showed  that  the  teaching
               materials for Chinese and Japanese Culinary obtained a score of 90.84% in the very
               good category and the learning design experts showed that the teaching materials
               with  a  score  of  95  categories  were  very  good.  Furthermore,  suggestions  from
               material experts need to be added to examples of images on the sub material for
               typical Japanese food ingredients.

               Keywords: Teaching materials, Development, Asian cuisine.










                                                44]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[The Implementation of Fussion Food Teaching Materials Based
                   on Local Bali Food in Vocational High School Students in
                                     Culinary Expertise

                        N W Sukerti  Cok Istri R Marsiti , Luh Masdarini , Damiati 4
                                 1,*
                                                            3
                                                2

               1,2,3,4 Vocational  Education  and  Culinary  Arts  Study  Program,  Faculty  of  Engineering  and  Vocational
               Studies, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: wayan.sukerti@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The present study aimed at describing (1) the results of the implementation of local food
               teaching  materials  seen  from  the  students'  practical  learning  outcomes,  (2)  learning  tools
               starting from the student worksheet and learning videos on the basic competency of fussion
               food for the 12th grade students of Vocational High School in Buleleng Regency, (3) students'
               responses toward local food teaching materials used in the 12th grade learning fussion food.
               Teaching materials can facilitate students to explore the material for developing fusion food
               learning.  Furthermore,  the  obstacle  in  the  development  and  use  of  local  food  teaching
               materials, namely the COVID-19 pandemic condition which makes it impossible to present
               students as a whole in class. This research was developmental research using ADDIE model.
               The subjects of this research were teachers, research team, and students. The number of
               respondents  were  36  people.  Data  were  collected  by  conducting  observation  and
               questionnaire  methods.  Data  were  analysed  by  using  descriptive  analysis  technique.  The
               results of study showed that: (1) the implementation of local food teaching materials through
               practical learning activities of Fusion Food at four vocational schools in Buleleng district could
               be  declared  successful  based  on  the  results  of  the  students’  practice  performance
               assessment on each dish considering 4 aspects, namely aspects of color, taste, texture, and
               presentation.  In  the  salad  dish  with  an  average  score  of  3.78  was  categorized  into  good
               category, soup with an average score of 3.80 was categorized into a good category, main
               course with a score of 3.77 was categorized into a good category, and dessert with a score of
               3.72  was  categorized  into  a  good  category,  (2)  the  fusion  food  learning  tools  had  been
               arranged based on local Balinese food ingredients, starting from the students’ worksheet and
               food learning media (learning videos), (3) students’ responses to teaching materials used as
               teaching materials to support practical activities were positive.

               Keywords: Teaching material of local food, Implementation of Balinese fussion food skills.







                                                45]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[Predictors of Health-Related Fitness Among First-Year College
                                          Students

                                 Aisha Sevilleja  Shirley Kerchaten 2
                                           1,*

               1,2  Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University

               * Corresponding author. Email: asevilleja@dmmmsu.edu.ph


                                           Abstract
               Because of the existence of the COVID-19 pandemic, the students were required to stay at
               home and adopt a flexible learning modality to continue their education. Ensuring physical
               wellness is necessary despite the different health protocols implemented. This study explored
               the  predictors  of  health-related  physical  fitness  among  first-year  college  students  in  a
               Philippine State University. It surveyed 158 students using an online platform (Google Form
               and Meet). Findings revealed that psychological well-being, socio-economic status, and sex
               were  all  predictors  of  health-related  physical  fitness.  Their  health-related  physical  fitness
               levels range from low to average; most of them belong to low socio-economic status, and
               psychological well-being is moderately high. Implications for practice were provided.

               Keywords:  COVID-19,  Physical-Health  Related  Fitness,  Psychological  Well-being,
               Socioeconomic Status.























                                                46]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[Empowerment of Balinese Local Wisdom and Important
                  Elements of Community Life As Learning Sourcesin of IPS
                                         SMP/MTs.
                                    in Buleleng Regency

                    I Wayan Kertih  I Gede Astra Wesnawa  I Putu Sriartha  Tuty Maryati 4
                                                             3,
                                                 2,
                              1,*

               1,2,3,4 Program Studi S2 PIPS Pascasarjana, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: wayankertih@gmail.com


                                           Abstract
               This study aimed at identifying and analyzing the forms of Balinese local wisdom
               and  important  elements  of  community  life  that  can  be  used  as  a  supplement  to
               social studies material for SMP/MTs. This study was a library research design. The
               object of study consists of curriculum documents, textbooks of local wisdom of the
               community, and important elements of community life. Data collection techniques
               were applied interviews, observations, documentation studies, and expert judgment.
               The data collected was in the form of qualitative data. Processing data used non-
               statistical analysis. The results of the study indicated that there were various local
               wisdom  and  important  elements  of  community  life  that  could  be  developed  as  a
               supplement of teaching materials in social studies learning at SMP/MTs. in Buleleng
               Regency, Bali Province.

               Keywords: Balinese local wisdom, Learning resources, Social studies learning for
               SMP/MTs.















                                                47]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[TBLA-Based Reflective Learning Model Analysis is Effective as a
                  Technique for Strengthening Students’ Pattern of Learning

                 Ni Ketut Suarni  Gede Nugraha Sudarsana  I Wayan Sujana  Ketut Susiani
                                                                         4,
                            1,*
                                                              3,
                                                 2,
                                   I Gusti Agung Ayu Wulandari 5

               1,2 Guidance and Counseling Department, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia
               3,4,5 Elementary School Teacher Education Department, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali,
               Indonesia


               * Corresponding author. Email: niketut.suarni@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The  purpose  of  this  study  was  to  analyze  the  effective  transcript-based  lesson
               analysis (TBLA) based reflective learning model as a technique for strengthening
               the pattern of learning for elementary school students Cluster IV Buleleng District.
               This is done through analysis of learning outcomes using transcripts of the results of
               conversations  in  learning  between  students  and  students,  students  and  teachers
               through in-depth observation, followed by analyzing learning transcripts. The sample
               of  this  research  was  elementary  school  students  in  Cluster  IV,  Buleleng  District,
               which were selected by random sampling of 50 people. The design of this study
               used a post-test control group design. The research data were analyzed using a t-
               test. The result of the research is that the TBLA based reflective learning model is
               effective  as  a  technique  for  strengthening  the  pattern  of  learning  for  elementary
               school students with the value of t-count = 2.413 > t-table = 2.011. The results of the
               study have implications as an alternative reference in developing teacher reflective
               learning  activities  in  strengthening  the  character  of  students  according  to  the
               demands  of  the  era  of  society  5.0,  through  various  behaviors  to  strengthen  the
               pattern of learning of elementary school students.

               Keywords: TBLA, Pattern of learning.











                                                48]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[Enhancing EFL Students’ Speaking Competency Through
                                  Animated Learning Video

                         Luh Gede Eka Wahyuni  Ni Putu Astiti Pratiwi 2
                                              1,*

               1,2 English Language Education Study Program, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali,
               Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: ekawahyuni@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               Communicative  competence  seems  to  be  a  major  issue  to  achieve  by  primary
               students in learning English in online learning process during COVID-19 outbreak.
               This is due to the lack of English exposure and innovative learning media which
               relate to 21st century learning. For this reason, this sequential explanatory mixed-
               method study was conducted to investigate the effectiveness of animated learning
               video upon students’ speaking competency and to describe their responses. Divided
               into two groups, 70 upper-class students in suburban primary schools participated
               as the subject. Test, questionnaire, and interview were used to collect the data. The
               data of the test were analyzed by using a t-test formula to investigate whether there
               was  a  significant  difference  in  students’  speaking  competency  between  the  two
               groups. The data of the questionnaire and interview were analyzed descriptively to
               see students’ responses towards the effectiveness of animated learning video. The
               statistical analysis showed that tobs value of Sig. (2 tailed) was .011 which means
               that  there  is  a  significant  difference  in  students’  speaking  competency.  The
               animated learning videos help them pronounce the words properly, improve their
               vocabulary mastery, be familiar with the structure, and be gradually more fluent in
               speaking.  In  short,  animated  learning  video  is  appropriate  to  enhance  students’
               speaking.

               Keywords: English learning, Speaking competency, Animated learning video.












                                                49]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[T Boosting The Quality of EFL Class through
                             HOTS-based English Activity Book:
                    Upgrading Independent Active Class during Pandemic

                             I Nyoman Adi Jaya Putra  Putu Kerti Nitiasih
                                                              2,
                                               1,
                         Ni Luh Putu Era Adnyayanti  Luh Gd. Rahayu Budiarta 4
                                             3,*

               1,2,3,4  Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: era.adnyayanti@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               Adapting to rapid changes of technology and information in the midst of Covid-19
               spread  requires  the  quality  improvement  of  students  learning  independently.
               Therefore,  students  need  an  appropriate,  challenging,  and  meaningful  support  to
               boost  their  English  learning  process.  This  study  aims  to  develop  a  HOTS-based
               English activity book for students grade 6 elementary school. This study uses D&D
               research  and  combined  with  ADDE  model  (Analysis,  Design,  Development,  and
               Evaluation). The product result of this research is still in the form of prototypes and it
               was tested by using the Expert Test and User Test. The result of the test shows that
               English  Activity  Book  is  very  relevant  and  suitable  for  students’  need.  While  the
               quality  of  product  indicates  that  it  is  categorized  as  an  “excellent  activity  book,”
               which can increase students' high-order thinking skill (HOTS).

               Keywords: English activity book, independent learning, HOTS.

















                                                50]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[A Need Analysis in English Material for XI Grade of Beauty
                                Program at SMK N 2 Singaraja

                       N.KWedhanti , D.A Eka Agustini , I Nym Pasek Hadi Saputra ,
                                               2
                                                                   3
                                 1
                                     I P N Wage Myartawan 4

               1,2,3 English Language Education, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia


               * Corresponding author. Email: karina.wedhanti@undiksha.ac.id , eka.agustini@undiksha.ac.id ,
               wmyartawan@undiksha.ac.id , hadi.saputra@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               This  research  was  aimed  at  investigating  the  English  material  and  analyzing  the
               appropriateness  of  English  teaching  material  based  on  ESP  principles.  This
               research used a qualitative descriptive method. The subject of this study was the
               eleventh  grade  students  of  beauty  program  in  SMK  N  2  Singaraja.  The  used  of
               Questionnaire and document checklist as the instruments for collecting the data.
               The result showed that the students needed English specific material and specific
               English  skill  in  tourism  field  especially  in  beauty  spa.  Furthermore,  based  on
               document  checklist,  English  teaching  material  in  beauty  program  was  not
               appropriate  with  the  ESP  concepts  because  the  data  showed  that  the  teaching
               material  was  too  general  and  did  not  close  to  the  students’  field.  Therefore,  to
               increase their competence in beauty spa activities, the beauty students hoped that
               the school can design an ESP program.

               Keywords: ESP, Need analysis, Learning need.
















                                                51]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[Developing Students’ Worksheet HOTS-Based English Learning
                       for Fourth Grade Students of Elementary School

                  Putu Kerti Nitiasih , Luh Gd Rahayu Budiarta  Ni Luh Putu Era Adnyayanti 3
                                                   2,*
                               1

               1,2,3  Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: rahayu.budiarta@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The  revised  2013  curriculum  in  Indonesia  emphasizes  HOTS-based  learning.
               Therefore, the teacher’s skill, techniques, methods, media, and books must support
               the student’s critical thinking. In the learning process, the teacher usually uses the
               student’s  worksheet.  However,  some  educational  practitioners  are  not  convinced
               that the activities contain of student’s worksheet appropriate with the HOTS criteria.
               Based on the researcher’s observation, there are many questions with LOTS types
               especially  in  multiple-choice  questions  for  students.  This  study  was  aimed  at
               developing students’ higher order thinking skills in English learning process through
               the use of students’ worksheets for fourth-grade students at the elementary school
               level.  This  study  used  the  ADDE  models  (Analysis,  Design,  Development,  and
               Evaluation).  The  teacher  and  the  fourth-grade  elementary  school  students  in
               Buleleng Regency were involved as the object of this study. The HOTS students’
               worksheets based on English learning were arranged by considering the adapted
               blue print from 4th grade English syllabus. The data were collected through several
               techniques, such as; observation, interview, document analysis, expert judgment,
               and  questionnaire.  The  result  of  this  study  showed  that  this  book  gave  positive
               response by stating that the book was categorizes as excellent in which it presented
               the material based on the syllabus and it had an interesting design. The HOTS’
               worksheet book that was developed in this study was expected as a medium for
               learning English that facilitated elementary school teachers and students.

               Keywords: Students’ worksheet, HOTS based English learning, elementary school
               students.









                                                52]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[Mobile Assisted Language Learning in Distance Learning:
                         Learning Process and Students’ Perception

                            Putu Adi Krisna Juniarta  Dewa Komang Tantra 2
                                             1,*

               1,2 Universitas Pendidian Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: adiputu108@gmail.com


                                           Abstract
               This study aims at determining how Mobile Assisted Language Learning application
               was implemented in the teaching and learning process and how the seventh grade
               students of SMP Negeri 4 Singaraja perceive the use of MALL in the teaching and
               learning  process  of  English  course.  Mixed-method  was  used  in  this  study.  The
               subjects were two English teachers who taught in 7th grade class and 7th grade
               students of SMP N 4 Singaraja. The object of this research was the implementation
               of MALL application in the process of teaching and learning English at 7th grade of
               SMP Negeri 4 Singaraja and their perceptions to the use of MALL in the teaching
               and learning process. The data were collected by using two instruments, namely
               observation  sheet  and  questionnaires.  Observation  sheet  was  used  to  record
               teachers’ activities in implementing MALL and questionnaires were used to find out
               student perception on those activities. As the results the teachers used MALL as a
               medium  for  sending  and  receiving  assignments  or  tests.  On  the other  hand,  the
               results  of  questionnaires  showed  that  the  7th  grade  students  gave  positive
               perception to the implementation of MALL in the teaching and learning process. It
               was indicated by the mean score of 3.20 that was categorized as positive perception
               comparing to the criteria. From the result, it could be concluded that most of the
               students agreed with the statement contained in the questionnaire so that they were
               able to get the mean score which classified the positive criteria.

               Keywords: MALL, Perception, Language learning.











                                                53]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[Developing a Student Management Model Based on Balinese
                                       Local Wisdom

                  Anak Agung Gede Agung  I Made Yudana I Gusti Ketut Arya Sunu Kadek
                                     1,*
                                                 2,
                                                                    3,
                              Rihendra Dantes I Gde Wawan Sudatha 5
                                           4,

               1,2 Universitas Pendidian Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: agung2056@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               In  the  Covid-19  pandemic  situation,  various  obstacles  occurred  in  various  life
               activities,  including  learning  activities  in  the  world  of  education.  In  this  covid-19
               pandemic,  education,  especially  in  junior  high  schools,  is  facing  difficulties  in
               managing student subjects or students as a result of not being able to have direct
               contact between educators and students. In the midst of the Covid-19 pandemic, we
               still  have  to  give  serious  attention  to  the  character  of  our  students  at  school,
               especially at the Singaraja City State Junior High School. We are well aware that
               the current character of the millennial generation shows symptoms such as: various
               types  of  violence,  both  physical,  psychological,  and  even  sexual  violence,
               deviations, insubordination, violations, abuses, and various frauds are some of the
               words that describe the problems that still occur in Indonesia. schools, especially
               junior high schools. This research is a development research that aims to produce a
               theoretical concept of a Local Wisdom-Based Student Management Model to Build
               a  Character  School  Culture  in  the  Covid-19  pandemic  through  library  research,
               comparative studies, and field surveys. The results of the study are as follows: (1)
               based on the results of the FGD which was attended by principals, vice principals,
               guardian teachers, committees, and student councils, it can be concluded that the
               values of Balinese Local Culture (KLBB) are all human creations, both in the form of
               physical and non-physical works that are inherited from generation to generation
               and  have  elements  of  noble  values  for  the  Hindu  community  in  Bali,  and  (2)
               Balinese Cultural Local Wisdom which is applied in student management among
               Singaraja City Junior High Schools can be formed as subhasita (aporism). in the
               form of short sentences or words that have noble values that have been and are
               being implemented by the Balinese community.

               Keywords: Student management, Local wisdom, Character.




                                                54]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[Readability of English Teacher Assessment Literacy Instrument
                                   in Indonesian Context

                 A.A. Gede Yudha Paramartha  Ni Luh Putu Eka Sulistia Dewi  Luh Gede Eka
                                       1,*
                                                               2
                                          Wahyuni 3

               1 Universitas Pendidian Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: yudha.paramartha@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               Many  studies  have  pointed  out  that  the  assessment  practices  by  teachers  in
               Indonesia were considered low. This arises a question why it happened. That is why
               the  Teacher  Assessment  Literacy  (TAL)  need  to  be  studied  more  deeply.
               Measurement  of  TAL  is  necessary  to  provide  a  clearer  picture  of  assessment
               practices especially by English teachers in Indonesia. With the existence of accurate
               measurement  standard,  it  is  expected  that  stakeholders  can  make  a  form  of
               intervention for teachers to improve the quality of teacher assessment practices. To
               answer this question, we developed an instrument for TAL based on Indonesian
               context.  The  focus  of  this  study  is  to  assess  the  readability  of  the  developed
               instrument by consulting the draft to two assessors. Both were asked to read each
               item in the instrument then gave an assessment of the readability into four criteria:
               highly readable, readable, somewhat difficult, and very difficult. The results show
               that most of the items (70%) were categorized ‘highly readable’, while no item was
               categorized ‘very difficult’. Some items were also discussed as examples to give
               clearer pictures on the readability of the developed instrument.

               Keywords: English, Readability,Teacher assessment literacy.













                                                55]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[Discipline of Fitnes Members in the
                        Adaptation of New Habits in Buleleng Regency

                     Made Agus Wijaya  Putu Panca Adi  Kadek Yogi Parta Lesmana 3
                                   1,*
                                                2,

               1 Universitas Pendidian Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: wijaya.madeagus@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               Physical activity, still needs to be carried out during the Covid-19 pandemic to keep
               the body healthy and fit. One of the physical activities carried out by the Buleleng
               community  is  fitness.  The  purpose  of  this  study  was  to  obtain  empirical  data
               regarding the level of discipline of fitness members during the adaptation period of
               new  habits  in  Buleleng  Regency.  This  descriptive  study  uses  simple  random
               sampling with a total sample of 99 people. The research instrument was a closed
               questionnaire in the form of a google form. Data were analyzed using qualitative
               descriptive techniques. The results showed: 49 people (49.49%) fitness members
               included in the very disciplined category, 38 people (38.38%) including discipline,
               11 people (11.11%) including moderately disciplined, and            1 person (1.01 %)
               including lack of discipline. Based on data analysis and discussion, the conclusion
               of this study is that the discipline of fitness members during the adaptation period of
               new  habits  in  Buleleng  Regency  is  included  in  the  discipline  category.  It  is
               recommended to the people of Buleleng Regency to continue to carry out physical
               activities by implementing strict health protocols.

               Keywords: covid, discipline, fitness.















                                                56]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[Identification of Individual Intolerance Behavior Trends Through
                         Thematic Apperception Test (TAT) Analysis

                             Gede Nugraha Sudarsana * Ni Ketut Suarni 2
                                                 1,

               1 Universitas Pendidian Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: nugraha.sudarsana@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               This  study  aims  to  describe  the  tendency  of  high  school  students'  intolerance
               behavior  by  using  Thematic  Apperception  Test  (TAT)  analysis.  This  research  is
               descriptive.  The  sample  in  this  study  were  high  school  /  vocational  students  in
               Singaraja  City,  and  data  reduction  was  carried  out  using  random  sampling.
               Obtained a sample of 120 students from 3 schools. Data was collected using the
               Thematic Apperception Test. Data analysis uses categorization of the total score
               obtained by respondents based on TAT answers. Based on the results of the study,
               it was obtained that the indicators of the tendency of intolerance were dominated by
               the following indicators: insecure by 87%, aggression by 75%, assumptions by 70%,
               prejudice by 60%, and jealousy by 57%. So it can be concluded that the Thematic
               Apperception  Test  (TAT)  analysis  can  be  used  to  identify  individual  intolerance
               behavior  tendencies.  These  findings  describe  the  manifestation  of  intolerance
               behavior that is interrelated between one indicator and another. The results of this
               study can be initial findings as an assessment method for educational institutions
               and related agencies in minimizing and capturing negative behavior.

               Keywords: Intolerance, Tolerance, Thematic apperception test.














                                                57]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[Nutritional and Organoleptic Quality of Tempe Now With the
                            Addition of Natural Dyeing Ingredients

                                     Damiati  Made Suriani 2
                                           1,

               1,2 Prodi Pendidikan Vokasional Seni Kuliner, Fakultas Teknik dan Kejuruan, Universitas Pendidikan
               Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: damiati@undiksha.ac.id, made.suriani@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               This study aims to determine (1) the nutritional quality of tempeh noodle products
               with the addition of natural dyes (moringa leaf extract, beetroot extract, and dragon
               fruit peel extract), (2) determine the quality of the organoleptic test (taste, color, and
               texture) on the product. tempeh noodles with the addition of natural coloring agents
               (moringa leaf extract, beetroot extract, and dragon fruit skin extract). dragon fruit, at
               a very high protein content is the addition of natural coloring ingredients of beetroot
               extract, which is 27.36% wt. The organic quality of tempe noodle products using
               natural natural coloring ingredients dragon fruit peel extract in terms of color, taste,
               and texture has a very favorable value. The natural coloring ingredients of Moringa
               leaf extract, beetroot and dragon fruit skin in tempe noodle products have nutritional
               quality (protein and fat), namely the natural coloring material of Moringa leaf extract
               while  the  excellent  rganoleptic  quality,  especially  in  the  natural  coloring  agent  of
               dragon fruit peel extract.

               Keywords: Nutritional quality, Organoleptic quality, Natural dyes.

















                                                58]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[Development of Tourism Master Plan in Panji Anom Village,
                            Sukasada District, Buleleng Regency

                                Wahjoedi , I Putu Panca Adi , Damiati 3
                                      1
                                                    2

               1,2 Jurusan Pendidikan Olahraga FOK, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia
               3 Jurusan Teknologi Industri FTK, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: wahjoedi@undiksha.ac.id, panca.adi@undiksha.ac.id,
               damiati@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               This development research aims to produce a master plan for tourism development
               in Panji Anom Village, Sukasada, Buleleng, Bali. The determination of Panji Anom
               Village as the research location was due to 1) well as the lack of support from the
               Panji Anom Village Government and other tourism stakeholders. , 2) Panji Anom
               Village has been established as a unit of watershed area (DAS) which is the locus
               for the development of cooperation with Undiksha, and 3) On a micro scale in the
               previous year, research and PkM activities have been carried out in Panji Anom
               Village  but  have  not  touched  the  level  umbrella  program  and  master  plan  for
               pioneering  and  developing  tourism  in  an  integrated  and  complete  manner.  This
               research produces First, the main tourism potential map of Panji Anom Village is 1)
               Nature tourism, especially "Panorama Puncak Landep", 2) Trekking, 3) Camping, 4)
               Agriculture, and 5) Honey bee cultivation, 6) Religious tourism, and 7) Pilot breeding
               of  rare  animals  in  forest  areas  managed  by  LPHD.  Second,  maps  of  5  trekking
               routes  that  are  worthy  of  sale  for  tourists  with  their  own  characteristics  and
               uniqueness, namely: 2 maps short trips, 2 maps of medium routes medium trips,
               and 1 long trip.

               Keywords: Master plan, Tourism development.













                                                59]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[Big Data for Indonesian Marine Fisheries
                                 a Preliminary Research Plan

                        Ni Putu Novita Puspa Dewi ,* I Putu Budhi Darma Purwanta 2
                                           1

               1 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia
               2  Universitas Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: novita.puspa.dewi@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               As a maritime country, Indonesia has a wider water area than the land area, but the
               number  of  fishermen  has  decreased  every  year  which  indicates  the  welfare  of
               fishermen has also decreased. On the other hand, the growth and development of
               marine data from various institutions in Indonesia has increased rapidly, supported
               by streaming data. However, these data have not been managed optimally or just
               left alone. The data can be used to help the performance of the fishermen so that
               they  can  improve  their  standard  of  living.  The  huge  and  diverse  amount  of  data
               requires the use of technology to extract data from many sources so as to analyze it
               in order to find potential problem-solving solutions. This study proposes an initial
               design for big data technology with an architecture designed to be able to overcome
               the problems of Indonesian marine fisheries.

               Keywords:  Big  data,  Big  data  application,  Maritime  applications,  Oceanographic
               data,



















                                                60]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[The Effectiveness of Blended Training in The Development of
                     Rock Climbing Athletes in Buleleng Regency In 2021

                                I Putu Panca Adi , Wahjoedi , Damiati 3
                                            1
                                                    2

               1,2 Department of Sports Education FOK, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia
               3 Department of Industrial Technology FTK, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: drsputupancaadi@gmail.com, wahjoedi@undiksha.ac.id,
               damiati@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               This research is a type of survey research conducted at FPTI Buleleng Regency,
               Bali  Province.  The  purpose  of  this  study  was  to  determine  the  effectiveness  of
               blended training in the development of rock climbing athletes in Buleleng Regency
               in 2021. The focus of the mapping includes anthropometric aspects and dominant
               physical  components  in  rock  climbing.  Data  collection  was  carried  out  using
               practical  test  methods  in  the  field  which  included  tests:  Anthropometry,  Sit  Ups,
               Push Ups, Stork Stands, Sit and Reach, Sprint Runs, and vertical jumps. The data
               analysis technique used descriptive statistical analysis with percentages. Based on
               the results of the study, it can be concluded that in the anthropometric aspect, the
               athletes of FPTI Buleleng have an average height of 148.15 cm, and weight of 43.67
               kg. While in the aspect of the dominant physical component, the balance indicator,
               15  athletes  (0.58%)  managed  to  do  the  balance  test  perfectly,  and  11  people
               (0.42%) failed to do it perfectly. In the indicators of strength, flexibility, speed, and
               explosive  power,  as  many  as  5  athletes  (19.23%)  were  very  good,  15  people
               (57.69%) were good, 4 people (15.38%) were enough or medium, 2 people ( 7.69%)
               less.

               Keywords: Rock climbing, Lying down, Offline, Blended training.













                                                61]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[Home Care Service Application for Patients

                            Agus Aan Jiwa Permana  I Gede Partha Sindu 2
                                              1,*

               1,2 Informatics Engineering, Technical and Vocational Faculty, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha,
               Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

                 * Corresponding author. Email: agus.aan@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               IT development has entered into all aspects. One of them is in the health sector.
               The current problem is that people do not dare to go to hospitals, health centers, or
               clinics for fear of contracting Covid, especially for children and the elderly. This is
               the main reason for providing care to patients that can be done at home. Based on
               this, it is necessary to apply home care services to provide services to patients at
               home. This service needs to be socialized to the community, employees and teams
               must  be  equipped  with  home  care  knowledge  so  that  they  can  provide  good
               services. This research is a type of qualitative descriptive research with a holistic
               approach.  The  method  used  in  developing  the  application  is  Agile  Method,  with
               primary  and  secondary  data  support.  The  focus  of  development  is  patient
               management, so that patients can easily access applications without administration
               malfunction.  The  results  of  this  study  are  web-based  applications  with  a  testing
               process using the Whitebox and Blackbox methods with a feasibility value of 82.5%
               (Good category).

               Keywords: Online service, Patient medical Care, Home care application.


















                                                62]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[Interaction Patterns of SMA/SMK Students in Buleleng Regency
                 Based on Learning Styles in Online Learning Using LMS and
                                        Social Media

                           I G Sudirtha * I G P Sindu  A A J Permana  I Nur 4
                                    1,
                                                           3,
                                              2,

               1,2,3 Faculty of Engineering and Vocational, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia
               4  Faculty of Law and Social Sciences, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: gede.sudirtha@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The purpose of this study was to find out how the interaction patterns of high school
               / vocational students in Buleleng Regency were based on learning styles in online
               learning  using  LMS  and  social  media.  The  method  used  in  this  research  is  a
               descriptive  qualitative  approach.  After  filling  out  the  learning  style  questionnaire
               instrument  by  as  many  as  150  research  subjects  who  came  from  high  school  /
               vocational students throughout Buleleng district, then an analysis / calculation of the
               score  of  each  research  subject  was  carried  out.  The  results  of  the  analysis  of
               learning styles on SMA/SMK students in Buleleng district resulted in 54% Visual,
               36% Auditory, 10% Kinesthetic. Interaction patterns based on online learning styles
               using  social  media  obtained  results  of  57%  Visual,  23%  Auditory,  and  20%
               Kinesthetic. Based on the description of the learning outcomes between students
               who receive online learning using social media, it can be concluded that students
               with  auditory  and  visual  learning  styles  who  are  taught  using  the  online  learning
               model  have  a  superior  interaction  pattern,  but  the  Kinesthetic  learning  style  on
               social media is quite good.

               Keywords: Learning management system, Social media, Interaction patterns.














                                                63]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[Analysis and Simulation of Current Zero Crossing Time Interval
                                   Under Different Loads

                         Sutaya I Wayan  Ariawan Ketut Udy Nurhayata I Gede 3
                                    1,*
                                                    2,

               1,2,3 Electronics Engineering Department, Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: wsutaya@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               This paper discusses the use of zero-crossing in switching for three types of loads,
               namely  resistive,  inductive,  and  capacitive.  The  switching  process  using  zero
               crossings and not using zero crossings was simulated with MATLAB software and
               then the simulation results were analyzed. The results of the simulation and analysis
               show that in resistive loads with zero-crossing the switching process to break the
               connection  between  the  voltage  source  and  the  load  there  is  no  voltage  at  the
               terminals so as to prevent the occurrence of arcs in the switch device. Whereas
               inductive  loads,  the  use  of  zero-crossing  is  able  to  prevent  the  arcs  going  from
               source to load, but unfortunately because the current and voltage are in different
               phases, so when switching at the zero voltage point the current is not at zero, so the
               reverse current will be able to cause the arcs in the switch device. In capacitive
               loads, the addition of zero-crossing will prevent the occurrence of arcs in the switch
               device.  When  the  voltage  is  switched  at  zero,  it  means  that  the  voltage  on  the
               capacitive  load  is  also  at  zero.  The  reverse  voltage  of  a  capacitive  load  is
               determined by the final voltage of the source. The time interval for a voltage to zero
               is also shown in the simulation so that it can be used by electronics practitioners in
               building electronic devices that use switching for large currents.

               Keywords: Zero crossing, MATLAB, Different loads.












                                                64]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[The Implementation of Tri Hita Karana Culture-Based Character
                  Education at Pasraman Budi Pekerti, Kemenuh Village, Bali

                           Ida Bagus Putu Arnyana  Ida Ayu Made Istri Utami 2
                                             1,*

               1,2,3  Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: putu.arnyana@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The  aims  of  this  study  are  to  investigate  and  examine  the  implementation  of
               character  education  and  the  dimensions  of  characters  taught  at  Pasraman  Budi
               Pekerti  in  Kemenuh  Village.  The  type  of  this  study  is  qualitative  research.  The
               participants who were targeted to be educated at the Pasraman were teenagers
               from the village aged between 15 - 15 years. Village leaders from Kemenuh, who
               were actively involved in the implementation of the Pasraman served as research
               subjects. Yoga Asanas, ethics based on Hindu teachings, Nyastra, Dharma Gita,
               Mesatua, male and female skills, Tirtayatra, Ngayah, and community service were
               among the programs utilized at the Pasraman education. The basic principles of Tri
               Hita  Karana,  which  include  harmony  with  God,  harmony  with  other  people,  and
               harmony  with  the  environment,  were  the  foundational  ideals  used  in  character
               education at the Pasraman. Religion, nationalism, integrity, mutual cooperation, and
               independence  were  the  qualities  of  character  that  were  taught.  The  participants'
               character, according to the teachers, was in the "very good" category.

               Keywords: Characters, Pasraman, Tri hita karana.















                                                65]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[Forms of Rural Tourism and Creative Economy Development

                 I Gede Astra Wesnawa  Putu Indra Christiawan Luh Gede Erni Sulindawati 3
                                                     2,
                                  1,*

               1,2,3 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: astra.wesnawa@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               In general, this research aims to develop sustainable rural tourism as a driving force
               for the creative economy in an effort to overcome poverty. Specifically, the first year
               was carried out (1) identification of forms of tourism that have been developed in
               rural areas of Bali, (2) identification of forms of creative economic development in
               rural tourism development. To achieve this goal, tourism research was carried out
               using an interdisciplinary approach. The research population includes tourist villages
               spread across districts/cities in Bali Province. The selected tourist village in each
               district  location  was  determined  as  1  tourist  village  location,  except  for  Buleleng
               Regency  with  4  tourist  villages,  so  there  were  11  tourist  village  locations,  which
               were selected by purposive sampling technique. The sample of subjects consisted
               of the Head of Regency Tourism, Village Heads, Pokdarwis, Community Leaders,
               tourism  actors,  restaurant  owners,  hotels,  travel  agents,  and  the  surrounding
               community. Data was collected through interviews, documentation, observation, and
               FGD. The analytical method used is an interactive analysis of the Miles Huberman
               model. The results show: (1) the forms of tourism developed include the form of
               natural attractions, cultural attractions and artificial attractions based on the potential
               that exists in tourist villages and (2) forms of creative economic development in rural
               tourism development from same thing to buy, in the form of tour package Planting
               rice, plowing the fields, making handicrafts from vetiver, learning traditional arts, and
               culinary arts.

               Keywords: Buleleng, Creative economy development, Forms of rural tourism.










                                                66]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[Social Determination of Coastal Communities in Utilizing Coastal
                                         Resources

                            I Gede Astra Wesnawa  Putu Indra Christiawan 2
                                             1,*

               1,2 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: astra.wesnawa@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The  long-term  goal  of  this  research  is  to  design  a  model  of  coastal  community-
               based coastal development in Buleleng Regency. The method used in achieving the
               objectives  of  this  research  is  an  analytic  survey  with  a  population  of  coastal
               communities in Buleleng Regency. This analytical survey research uses a sample
               area with purposive sampling technique, with the consideration that the area is a
               coastal area that is built up as well as human intervention in utilizing resources in
               the  northern  coastal  area  of  Bali  Province.  Data  were  collected  using  FGD  data
               collection instruments, interviews and observations. Data analysis was carried out
               using  qualitative  analysis.  The  results  showed  that  the  social  determination  of
               coastal communities viewed from the aspects of culture, economy, education and
               behavior showed that awig-awig was effective in regulating community behavior in
               the use of the coastal environment, the economic aspect of the work of catching fish
               fishermen  was  no  longer  promising  to  meet  the  needs  of  life,  so  they  diverted
               activities as laborers or traders. The training that is followed can give birth to new
               entrepreneurs, but some have not been empowered and institutionalized from the
               training carried out, and the behavior of coastal communities shows concern for the
               environment through planting mangrove trees, coastal protection plants, and mutual
               cooperation.

               Keywords: Coastal, Environment, Social Determinants, Utilization of Coastal Resources.










                                                67]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[Analysis of Archives Management at Universitas Pendidikan
                                          Ganesha

                      Luh Putu Santiari  Sariyasa Sariyasa I Ketut Ngurah Arintasuta 3
                                  1,*
                                                 2,

               1,2,3 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: putu.santiari@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               This  article  is  the  result  of  research  for  a  thesis  entitled  "Analysis  of  Archive
               Management  at  Ganesha  Education  University."  This  study  aims  to  determine
               archive  management  by  Ganesha  Education  University  archivists  in  terms  of
               planning,  organizing,  directing  and  supervising.  To  achieve  these  objectives,  this
               research was designed using a qualitative approach. Information related to research
               data  was  obtained  from  informants  using  interviews  and  data  documentation
               available  at  the  Undiksha  archivist.  The  data  collected  will  then  be  selected  or
               reduced  according  to  the  research  objectives  and  presented  based  on  the
               dimensions of the research study to be concluded based on the research objectives.
               The results of this study indicate that archive management activities at Ganesha
               University  of  Education  are  viewed  from  the  aspects  of  planning,  organizing,
               directing,  supervising.  Based  on  the  results  of  research  conducted,  Undiksha
               Archives  have  carried  out  good  archive  management  functions,  starting  from
               planning, organizing, directing and managing.

               Keywords: Archives, Archives Management, Public Information.














                                                68]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[The Representation of Character Education in the
                 Characterization of Lily Owens in Sue Monk Kidd’s The Secret
                                     Life of Bees (2001)

                I Gusti Ayu Diah Gita Saraswati 1,  Ni Komang Arie Suwastini 2*,  Ida Ayu Made Istri Utami 3 , Ni Luh Putu Sri
                            Adnyani 4,  I Gusti Agung Sri Rwa Jayantini 5 , I Wayan Budiarta 6

               1,2,3,4  Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia
               5  Universitas Mahasaraswati, Denpasar, Bali, Indonesia
               6  Universitas Warmadewa, Denpasar, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: arie.suwastini@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               As literature is argued to bring positive character values while being an entertaining
               media for learning character education, the present study analyzed the five core
               values of character education in The Secret Life of Bees (2001). The study focused
               on the characterization of Lily Owens as the main character in representing good
               and bad characters in children. Descriptive qualitative was used to analyze the five
               core  values  of  character  education  and  sub-character  education  values.  The
               research found out that Lily Owens has all five core values of character education
               and 33 sub-character education values. Religious, independent, and integrity values
               are strongly identified when Lily lived in Boatwright house until the end of the story.
               Meanwhile, the cooperation and nationalism character values were not too strong
               identified  like  other  three  values.  Moreover,  there  are  two  values  of  character
               education identified have important role for Lily’s life development, such as religious
               and integrity values. Those characterizations are very necessary and beneficial for
               the young learner in determining positive and negative characters as guidance for
               acting,  communicating  and  thinking  in  real  life  situation.  For  additional,  parents,
               teachers, and stakeholders have important role to guide the young learner to gain
               better perspective of those five core character education values.

               Keywords: Five core values of character education, Main character, Novel.








                                                69]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[Why Students Should Like to Have Severus Snape As a Teacher?

                Ni Komang Arie Suwastini ,* Luh Winda Agustina , Putu Yasamahadewi Ronald
                                                                     3,
                                   1
                                                     2
                       Umbas I Gusti Ayu Agung Dian Susanthi , Nice Maylani Asril 6
                                                     5
                            4,

               1,2,3,4,5 ,6 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia
               4  School for Socio-Political Science Wira Bakti, Denpasar, Bali, Indonesia
               5  Universitas Warmadewa, Denpasar, Bali, Indonesia


               * Corresponding author. Email: arie.suwastini@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               J.K Rowling’s Harry Potter and the Philosopher’s Stone has successfully attracted
               readers by the presence of Severus Snape with his complex characterizations which
               enriched the values of the story. Severus Snape was depicted as a hero who got
               hated and misjudged by the students because of his ambiguous behaviors. This
               study aimed at describing the values of character education reflected in Severus
               Snape’s characterizations showing that he was a good teacher despite of him being
               suspected as the villain by using the theory of 18 values of character education
               stated by Ministry of National Education (2010). The data will be analyzed by using
               the model of qualitative research from Miles, Huberman, and Saldaña (2014). As the
               result, 4 values including discipline, hardworking, social awareness, and responsible
               are reflected in his characterizations proving that Severus Snape is a good teacher
               despite of his nature as an unfriendly individual. Therefore, rather than complaining
               his  nature  as  a  human  being,  students  should  be  happy  to  have  a  teacher  as
               Severus Snape.

               Keywords: Characterizations, Character education, Harry Potter, Philosopher’s Stone.















                                                70]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[Web-Based System for Bali Tourism Sentiment Analysis
                 during The Covid-19 Pandemic using Django Web Framework
                                  and Naive Bayes Method


                        Gede Aditra Pradnyana , I Gede Mahendra Darmawiguna 2
                                          1
               1,2  Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha

               * Corresponding author. Email: gede.aditra@undiksha.ac.id


                                           Abstract
               The province of Bali, which relies heavily on the tourism sector, is certainly affected
               by  the  Covid-19  pandemic.  The  various  policies  taken  by  the  Bali  Provincial
               Government  in  order  to  break  the  chain  of  the  spread  of  Covid-19  always
               experience pros and cons in the community. The data from the analysis of public
               opinion on social media can be used as feedback to the government. The results of
               the analysis of social media data can be used as consideration for formulating more
               targeted policies. Analyzing public opinion on social media is not an easy thing. The
               challenges of processing opinion data from social media include the large amount of
               data  that  requires  high  costs  such  as  time  and  effort  if  you  have  to  analyze  it
               manually one by one. The problem is complicated by dirty opinion data because it
               does not use standard language. In this study, a web-based system was developed
               to analyze Bali tourism sentiment using the Naïve Bayes method. The web-based
               system was developed with the Django web framework with a waterfall software
               development model. The results of testing the accuracy of the Naïve Bayes Method
               in conducting sentiment were obtained at 83.47%.

               Keywords:  Bali  Tourism,  Sentiment  Analysis,  Covid-19,  Naïve  Bayes,  Django  Web
               Framework










                                                71]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[Numerical Simulation and Sensitivity Analysis of
                              Dengue Model with Vector Control

                                       Ronica de Leon 1,*

               1 Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University

               * Corresponding author. Email: rmasangkay@dmmmsu.edu.ph


                                           Abstract
               Dengue remains a threat in human health and epidemic can still occur especially on
               rainy  seasons.  In  this  study,  a  mathematical  model  for  dengue  was  developed
               incorporating vector control strategy. The behaviour of solutions and sensitivities of
               state variables were investigated. Through numerical simulation it was shown that
               when the computed reproduction number is less than one the solution approaches
               the disease-free equilibrium. If the computed reproduction number exceeds one, the
               solution does not approach endemic equilibrium. Relative sensitivities showed that
               prevention methods introduced can mitigate the spread of the disease but between
               the nonchemical strategy and chemical strategy, the parameter relating to the latter
               is more influential to the behaviour of solution of the system.

               Keywords: Mathematical model, vector control strategy, equilibrium, sensitivity.



















                                                72]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[Diversity of Trees and Shrubs in DMMMSU-NLUC Forest

                           Karen Ballada  Mark Kevin Lopez  Jaures Nalica 3
                                                    2,
                                      1,*

               1 Department of Biology, College of Arts and Sciences, Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University

               * Corresponding author. Email: kballada@dmmmsu.edu.ph


                                           Abstract
               Due to its rapid loss, it is necessary to document what remains of our biodiversity.
               This  study  aimed  to  document  the  floral  diversity  of  the  forest  surrounding
               DMMMSU-NLUC. Six sampling plots (20mx20m) were established and trees and
               shrubs  were  documented,  identified  and  counted.  Importance  values  and
               biodiversity indices of the identified trees and shrubs were determined and soil pH
               and  moisture  content  were  also  determined.  Results  revealed  that  there  are  58
               identified trees and shrubs belonging to 26 families consisting of 42 tree species
               and 16 shrubs. Majority of them are native plants (40 species), 4 are exotic, 4 are
               naturalized, and 1 is invasive. Eleven of the identified species are threatened: 2 are
               endangered,  6  are  vulnerable,  2  are  other  threatened  species,  and  1  is  near
               threatened. The presence of threatened species in the forest could be attributed to
               natural and anthropogenic factors such as over collection, limited distribution range,
               deforestation, and introduction of exotic species. The four dominant tree and shrub
               species  are  Caryota  cumingii  (fishtail  palm),  Pterocarpus  indicus  (narra),
               Semecarpus  cuneiformis  (kamiring),  Melicope  triphylla,  Psychotria  luzoniensis
               (katagpong gubat), Glochidion luzonense (kakadli), Tabernaemontana pandacaqui
               (kuribetbet),  and  Scolopia  luzonensis  (palutan).  All  are  native  species,  3  are
               endemic and 5 are indigenous. The forest around DMMMSU-NLUC is still rich in
               biodiversity. The pH of 6.1 and moisture content of 21.4% of soil sampled from the
               forest are within the normal range for plants to thrive.

               Keywords: Threatened, Endangered, Endemic, Indigenous, Native species.











                                                73]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[Content Analysis of the K to 12 World History Teaching Guides
                              in terms of Teaching Approaches

                                        Arnie G. Dizon 1*

               1  College of Education, South La Union Campus, Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University,
               Philippines

               * Corresponding author. Email: adizon@dmmmsu.edu.p


                                           Abstract
               This study is a content analysis of the Philippines Department of Education K to 12
               World History teaching guides, focusing on teaching approaches geared towards
               the  development  of  historical  thinking  skills  among  Grade  8  students.  Learning
               activities purposively chosen by the researcher were categorized and coded using
               ATLAS.ti,  a  qualitative  data  analysis  software.  Then,  themes  that  emerged  were
               validated by three historians. Results show more emphasis on the Inquiry approach
               while there is lesser emphasis on the Multidisciplinary approach. This means that
               students could easily identify continuity and change as teaching guides are heavily
               oriented on the Inquiry approach, but they could hardly take historical perspectives
               due to limited activities based on Multidisciplinary approach. It is recommended that
               instructional material writers should give equal emphasis on teaching approaches
               indicated  in  the  curriculum.  This  is  to  provide  equal  opportunities  for  the
               development of various historical thinking skills.

               Keywords:  Content  analysis,  Historical  thinking  skills,  Teaching  approaches,  Teaching
               guides, World History.
















                                                74]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[Narrativizing Student Teachers’ Experiences
                                 of Teaching English Abroad

                                      Abelynn T. Llarenas
                                                     1*

               1  Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University

               * Corresponding author. Email:


                                           Abstract
               This  paper  described  the  experiences  teacher  education  program  graduates  in
               DMMMSU-SLUC  who  taught  English  in  Thailand  and  Vietnam  for  their  student
               teaching course under the Student Internship Abroad Program (SIAP). The study
               employed a qualitative methodology and descriptive phenomenology approach to
               capture  and  describe  the  experiences  of  the  participants.    The  data  was  from  a
               semi-structured interview and a survey questionnaire. Cool and warm analyses was
               used to analyze the data. This study yielded four themes: take off, turbulence, take
               on, and touchdown. Take off refers to the participants’ experiences at the onset of
               their internship in their host school. Turbulence refers to the challenges that they
               encountered in the course of their internship. The top challenges they faced were
               learners’ level of English, English skills, cultural differences, use of mother tongue in
               class, and language barrier. Take on refers to taking on or dealing with challenges.
               Touchdown  refers  to  the  reflections  and  realizations  that  they  had  after  the
               internship.

               Keywords: ASEAN, Internship abroad, Preservice teaching, SIAP, Take off,
               Turbulence, Take on, Touchdown.















                                                75]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[Isolation, Purification and Molecular Identification of Microfungi
                               from the Landfill Site of Bangar,
                                    La Union, Philippines

                               Mark Kevin Lopez  Francis Ruel Castillo 2
                                            1,*

               1  Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University
               2  University of the Philippines-Manila

               * Corresponding author. Email: mlopez@dmmmsu.edu.ph


                                           Abstract
               Fungi  represent  the  second  largest  group  of  eukaryotic  organisms  on  earth  with
               estimates  ranging  from  1.5  to  5.1  million  species.  Fungi  are  important  soil
               microorganisms for they play an important part in nutrition and processes affecting
               growth  and  development  of  plants.  The  used  of  various  molecular  methods  in
               identification of organism is proven to be fast, specific and sensitive. Up to date, it is
               still  powerful  in  resolving  disputes  among  erroneous  morphological  features  of
               closely related organismal species. The continued search for more potential fungal
               species that has wide range of benefits or applications is then necessary. Hence,
               this study isolated, purified and described the microfungi present from the landfill
               site of Bangar, La Union. Soil analysis was also conducted to determine the pH,
               organic  matter,  and  quantify  heavy  metal  present.  Molecular  identification  and
               phylogenetic analysis were carried out using the ITS region. BLASTn was used for
               ascertaining  the  fungal  identity  while  MEGA  11  was  used  for  the  alignment  and
               phylogenetic analysis. Soil analysis revealed that the pH, organic matter, and heavy
               metal concentration are within the permissible limits. Ten microfungal species were
               described  and  identified  belonging  to  four  genera  such  as  Actinomucor  (1),
               Acrophialophora  (1),  Aspergillus  (6),  Penicillium  (2).  Seven  species  were
               successfully sequenced, and phylogenetic analysis revealed monophyly in Aspergilli
               while Acrophialophora is distantly related to the other microfungal species.

               Keywords: ITS region, Microfungi, Molecular identification, Phylogenetic analysis.








                                                76]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[Community Management Information Systems
                               for the Municipality of Bacnotan

                                  Herve E. Orpilla  Daniel A. Neri 2
                                             1,*

               1,2  College of Information Systems, Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University – North La Union
               Campus

               * Corresponding author. Email: horpilla@dmmmsu.edu.ph


                                           Abstract
               Community  Management  Information  Systems  has  become  an  increasingly
               common way to distribute administrative data from local government units. These
               systems are using the administrative data to create and distribute valuable to the
               community  and  social  indicator  data  to  concerned  individuals,  social  service
               organizations,  community  developmentprofessionals,  and  planners.  This  paper
               aimed  to  develop  a  Community  Management  Information  System  (CMIS)  for  the
               Municipality of Bacnotan. Specifically, determine the level of usability of the CMIS
               for  the  Municipality  of  Bacnotan  as  to  efficiency,  affect,  control,  helpfulness,  and
               learnability. The study used the descriptive and developmental types of research
               with  the  documentary  checklist  and  survey  questionnaires  as  the  main  tools  in
               gathering data. A total of fifty-one (51) respondents were involved in the study. PHP
               as the Programming language used in developing the system and MySQL for the
               creation  of  database,  WAMP  as  the  database  server  used.  Data  gathered  were
               quantified  and  analyzed  using  frequency  counts  and  weighted  means.  Salient
               findings of the study showed that the Community Management Information System
               performs at its best and it is Usable, thus it was developed with the appropriate
               features and served its utility value and operated as it was intended for use.

               Keywords: Community management, Information systems, Local government unit.












                                                77]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[Determining a Vigorous Beehive Location thru Computer Vision
                                        Technology

                                       Stephan Kupsch 1,*

               1  Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University

               * Corresponding author. Email: skupsch@dmmmsu.edu.ph


                                           Abstract
               This study focused on the use of a lightweight script in computer vision technology
               to create a web app that can help beekeepers know the suitable location for their
               beehive. The general model was created in such a way that an image would be
               uploaded then assessed by the web app, which is the application's main feature.
               Because of the large size of aerial photos to be analyzed, the web app requires a
               7KB  lightweight  client-side  software  development  library/framework.  The  program
               has been implemented as a web application for the benefit of beekeepers with its
               ultra-fast functionality. It would be ideal nice to have a version for mobile devices for
               further recommendation. The program is the first to incorporate computer vision into
               beekeeping  information  technology.  HTML5,  XAMPP  ver.  3.2.4  Apache  and  My
               SQL were also used in this study for the development of the app with a drone that
               was  used  to  capture  images.  Moreoever,  this  study  also  used  feature-driven
               development methodology in the development of the web app. Results showed that
               a 7kb image size is also applicable in computer vision.

               Keywords: Machine learning, Computer vision, Lightweight scripting, Beehive.

















                                                78]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[Data Encryption Based on ERC5 Algorithm Ver. 2.0 for Self -
                                      Checkout Kiosk

                 Excel V. Cabrera  Jessie B. Vallecera Maricel O. Pre Krizia Ann E. Ramirez 4
                             1, *
                                             2,
                                                         3,

               1,2,3,4  College of Information Systems, Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University – North La Union
               Campus

               * Corresponding author. Email: ecabrera@dmmmsu.edu.ph


                                           Abstract
               Many shoppers opt to use procedures that do not require physical contact to other
               people, as much as possible, especially in this time of pandemic. Contactless mode
               of payment offers the convenience and added protection to the person that uses this
               method. However, malicious intents have been a threat to these kinds of system
               and data encryption has been a norm to secure these systems against such acts.
               This paper mainly focused on the implementation of the developed ERC5 algorithm
               version  2.0  in  a  self-checkout  kiosk  and  test  its  vulnerability.  This  study  used
               developmental and evaluative type of research with simulation system and online
               platforms as the main tools in gathering data. PHP and Node JS, XAMPP version
               3.2.2,  MySQL,  sublime,  RFID  reader,  RFID  cards,  Omnidirectional  USB  Barcode
               reader and thermal printer were the materials used in this study. This paper was
               able to implement the ERC5 algorithm ver. 2.0 as a data encryption protocol for the
               self-checkout kiosk and was able to pass the vulnerability test.

               Keywords: Checkout kiosk, Encryption, Self-checkout kiosk, Vulnerability test.

















                                                79]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[Congruence Properties of the Sum of Positive Powers
                                  of two Mersenne Primes

                                      William S. Gayo, Jr 1,*

               1  College of Arts and Sciences, Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University

               * Corresponding author. Email: wgayo@dmmmsu.edu.ph


                                           Abstract
               Special numbers are numbers with special properties. One of the special numbers is
               the Mersenne prime. It is a prime number of the form 2^p-1, where p is also a prime
               number. In this study, the sum of powers of two Mersenne primes is considered.
               The main goal is to find the congruence properties of the sum under consideration
               using modular arithmetic. It was found out that the sum of powers of the two said
               primes is either congruent to 1 or 3 (mod 4). Moreover, the sum of powers of large
               Mersenne  primes  (Mersenne  primes  greater  than  3)  is  congruent  to  2  (mod  6).
               Further, the same sum of powers is also congruent to 0, 2 or 6 (mod 8).

               Keywords: Mersenne primes, Congruence properties, Modular arithmetic method.






















                                                80]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[Technology and Livelihood Education
                             Program of Dmmmsu: Analysis and
                                       Enhancement

                                     Ana Liza O. Ordinario 1,*

               1  Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University

               * Corresponding author. Email: aordianrio@dmmmsu.edu.ph


                                           Abstract
               This  study  focused  on  analyzing  the  TLE  program  of  DMMMSU  with  75
               respondents, composed of 13 teachers and 62 students to address the low BLEPT
               passing rate and quality of teaching. The descriptive-survey method of investigation
               was  used  and  data  were  treated  using  frequency  counts,  percentages,  ranking,
               mean  and  weighted  mean  and  Spearman  Rank  Rho  Correlation.  The  teaching
               personnel were dominated by females, all licensed, generally married who were in
               the middle age with sufficient experiences. Most of them are post degree holders
               with salary grade from 12-16 and attended local seminars, with specialized training
               mostly in bread and pastry; however, awards received were rare. Teachers were
               found to be highly competent and highly utilizing various instructional pedagogies
               and likewise highly skilled in livelihood except in the area of dressmaking. The TLE
               students  were  mostly  from  lowincome  families  whose  parents  completed  high
               school  and  worked  as  farmers  and  housekeepers.  Students  were  rated  as
               moderately skilled in livelihood skills and in different competencies; hence, almost
               all  areas  were  categorized  as  constraints.  Tools  and  equipment  were  available,
               moderately adequate and moderately functional. The status of laboratory facilities
               has no relation to the level of livelihood skills of students and teachers. A validated
               Enhancement  Program  was  created  to  address  the  identified  constraints  and  to
               develop skills of both teachers and students.

               Keywords: BLEPT performance, Enhancement, Livelihood skills, Pedagogies, TLE program.









                                                81]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[Potential of Vetiver (Vetiveria zizanioides)
                                   on Leachate Treatment

                                 Celso Jucutan  Leonora Ngilangil 2
                                           1,*

               1  Celso Jucutan
               2  Leonora Ngilangil

               * Corresponding author. Email: cjucutan@dmmmsu.edu.ph


                                           Abstract
               Leachate from landfills contains a lot of toxic chemicals which requires management
               including its treatment. In this experimental study, the efficiency of vetiver (Vetiveria
               zizanioides)  in  removing  pollutants  was  pursued  to  determine  its  potential  on
               leachate treatment from two sanitary landfills. Specifically, it sought to determine the
               characteristics of the raw leachate samples and to determine the removal efficiency
               of  vetiver  on  pollutants  in  leachate  samples  after  30  to  60  days  retention  time.
               Vetiver growth in terms of length of roots and height of shoots was also determined.
               Results  revealed  that  raw  leachate  samples  from  Balaoan  Sanitary  landfill
               conformed  to  DAO  2016-08  effluent  standards  on  almost  all  parameters  except
               NH3-N  while  leachate  samples  from  the  City  of  San  Fernando  Sanitary  Landfill
               failed to conform to some parameters such as color, COD, and NH3-N, but were
               found  compliant  to  TSS,  NO3-N,  Pb,  Hg,  Total  Coliform  and  E.  Coli  permissible
               amounts.  Leachate  samples  from  Balaoan  Sanitary  Landfill  planted  with  vetiver
               showed  decreasing  trend  in  total  suspended  solids  after  30  days  retention
               compared to those without plant. After 60 days, both samples cultivated with vetiver
               passed the effluent standards except for color, pH and COD values for the CSFSLF
               leachate.  There  is  significant  growth  in  vetiver  grasses  cultivated  in  leachate
               samples from BSLF while the grasses in CSFSLF samples deteriorated and have
               been  poisoned  to  death  before  reaching  6  weeks  of  cultivation.  The  removal
               efficiency of vetiver in BSLF was noted high in Total Coliform (99.98 %), NH3-N
               (98.52%), and TSS (61.76%) after 30 days. On the other hand, removal efficiency of
               vetiver in CSFSLF leachate after 30 days was observed in NH3-N (56.94%), TSS
               (35.48%), and Conductivity (17.16%). After 60 days, the BSLF leachate sample with
               vetiver continued to have high removal efficiency for NH3-N (92.50%), and Nitrate-N
               (98.26%).

               Keywords: Leachate, Sanitary landfills, Treatment, Vetiver.




                                                82]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[Plausible Eclecticism
                   A Joint Venture Of Methods And Post-Method Pedagogy

                          A.A.N. Yudha Martin Mahardika , Ni Putu Astiti Pratiwi
                                                 1*
                                                                 2
               1, 2 Universitas Pendidikan Ganesha, Singaraja, Bali, Indonesia

               * Corresponding author. Email: yudha.martin@undiksha.ac.id

                                           Abstract
               This  is  a  state-of-the-art  article  proposing  the  use  of  plausible  eclecticism  as
               alternative  to  methods  of  teachings.  The  idea  of  plausible  eclecticism  is  to  gain
               valuable  contribution  of  various  methods  of  teaching,  while  minimizing  the
               drawbacks issues of each teaching method. The plausible eclecticism was triggered
               by  the  notions  of  post-method  pedagogy,  proposed  by  Kumaravadivelu.  Post-
               method has raised awareness of the limitation of methods and gives more attention
               to teachers’ autonomy to pragmatically theorize what they practice using the sense
               of plausibility. The proposed notions have gained debates. The debates on post-
               method notions should be positively responded through idea sharing. This article is
               written to share thoughts on the debates.

               Keywords: Plausible Eclecticism, Post-method, Teaching Method, Debate.






















                                                83]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[Understanding the Pedagogical Dilemma Using the KAP
                        (Knowledge, Attitude and Practice) Approach:
                         “What Will You Use?”“What Will You Use?”


                                        Jomar L. Aban
                                                  1,*
               1  Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University

               * Corresponding author. Email: jaban@dmmmsu.edu.ph

                                           Abstract
               The  complex  nature  of  the  teaching  and  learning  process  implies  tremendous
               diversity of teaching pedagogies. Using the KAP analysis, this study undermined the
               awareness, attitudes and utilization of the BSED (Bachelor in Secondary Education)
               educators in the four most commonly perceived teaching pedagogies in the tertiary
               level  namely:  lecture  method,  cooperative  learning,  inquiry-based  learning,  and
               learning  with  emphasis  on  communication  skills.  The  respondents  were  highly
               aware of the three learner-centered pedagogy but was ironically moderately aware
               of the traditional lecture method. It was also recognized that BSED educators were
               highly  engaged  to  the  cooperative  learning  pedagogy,  both  in  attitude  and  in
               practice.  The  KAP  analysis  was  triangulated  to  come  up  with  a  synergistic
               educational pedagogy that can be used by the BSED educators in the tertiary level.

               Keywords: Cooperative learning, KAP analysis, Lecture method, Teaching pedagogy.



















                                                84]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[Extraction of Dye from Weeds and Dyeing of Silk Yarn
                                 Degummed with Wood Ash

                          Raymund Sanchez  Delia V. Lopez Flory M. Libunao
                                                    2,
                                                                 3
                                       1,*
               1,2 Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University

               * Corresponding author. Email: rsanchez@dmmmsu.edu.ph

                                           Abstract
               This research was conducted to produce hand-woven silk shawls made of naturally
               dyed  silk  yarns  and  to  evaluate  the  level  of  acceptability.    Thrown  silk  was
               degummed in wood ash solution and dyed with three natural dyes extracted from
               hagonoy (Chromolaena odorata), tabukol (Portulaca oleracea) and lantana (Lantana
               camara). The dyed thrown silk was hand woven into shawls with a width of 36”and
               of length 78”. The acceptability of handwoven shawls was assessed as to texture,
               luster,  and  color.    The  findings  showed  significant  differences  among  the  three
               natural  dyes.  Based  on  their  high  level  of  acceptability  as  to  texture,  luster,  and
               color, the three natural dyes can be used to color silk yarn, which is then woven into
               a silk shawl.

               Keywords: Degumming, Hand-woven silk shawls, Natural dyes, Quality acceptability, wood
               ash solution.






















                                                85]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[English Grammar Proficiency of English Major College Students
                in the PhilippinesEnglish Grammar Proficiency of English Major
                             College Students in the Philippines


                    Maria Elaine D. Pinay-an  Rochelle M. Verganio Desiree E. Donato
                                       1,*
                                                                       3
                                                        2,

               1,2,3 Don Mariano Marcos Memorial State University

               * Corresponding author. Email: mpinay-an@dmmmsu.edu.ph

                                           Abstract
               The level of English proficiency of students could be attributed to the proficiency of
               the teachers teaching English. This paper aims to determine the English grammar
               proficiency  of  BSE  English  major  students  of  the  College  of  Education  in  Don
               Mariano  Marcos  Memorial  State  University  North  La  Union  Campus,  La  Union,
               Philippines.  Two  sets  of  data  are  utilized  for  analysis:  the  students’  grades  in
               English 100 and data of results in the English Language Proficiency Test conducted
               by  the  researchers.  The  study  utilized  the  descriptive  quantitative  correlational
               method  in  the  presentation  of  data.  Findings  reveal  that  there  is  a  need  for  an
               intervention program in order to enhance the English grammar proficiency of the
               soon to be English teachers.

               Keywords:  English  grammar  proficiency,  English  major  students,  English  grammar
               intervention, Philippines.






















                                                86]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[87]]></page></pages></Search>